<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
XVIII
About this time <persName n="60">Attalus III, king of Asia</persName>, the brother of <persName n="157">Eumenes II</persName>, died, and left the Roman people his heir. Thus Asia was added to the Roman empire by will.

XIX
Shortly after, also, <persName n="145">Decimus Brutus Gallaecus</persName> triumphed with great glory over the Gallaecians and Lusitanians; and <persName n="509">Scipio Aemilianus</persName> had a second triumph over the Numantines. in the fourteenth year after his first triumph for his exploits in Africa.

XX
A war in the meantime was kindled in Asia by <persName n="47">Aristonicus</persName>, the son of <persName n="157">Eumenes II</persName> by a concubine: this <persName n="157">Eumenes II</persName> was the brother of <persName n="60">Attalus III</persName>. Against him was sent out <persName n="452">Publius Licinius Crassus</persName>, who had ample assistance from several kings, for not only <persName n="383">Nicomedes</persName>, the king of Bithynia, supported the Romans, but also <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> king of Pontus, with whom they had afterwards a very great war, as well as <persName n="611">Ariarathes</persName>, king of Cappadocia, and <persName n="610">Pylaemenes</persName> of Paphlagonia. <persName n="452">Publius Licinius Crassus</persName> notwithstanding was defeated, and killed in battle; his head was carried to <persName n="47">Aristonicus</persName>, and his body buried at Smyrna. Soon after <persName n="404">Perpenna</persName>, the Roman consul, who was appointed successor to <persName n="452">Publius Licinius Crassus</persName>, hearing of the event of the war, hastened to Asia; and defeating <persName n="47">Aristonicus</persName> in battle, near the city Stratonice to which he had fled, reduced him by famine to surrender. <persName n="47">Aristonicus</persName>, by command of the senate, was strangled in prison at Rome; for a triumph could not be celebrated on his account, because <persName n="404">Perpenna</persName> had died at Pergamus on his return.

XXI
In the consulate of <persName n="358">Metellus Balearicus</persName> and <persName n="575">Titus Quinctius Flamininius</persName>, Carthage in Africa, which still exists, was rebuilt by order of the senate, two and twenty years after it had been destroyed by <persName n="509">Scipio Aemilianus</persName>. A colony of Roman citizens was sent out thither.

XXII
In the six hundred and twenty-seventh year from the founding of the city, <persName n="613">Caius Cassius Longinus</persName> and <persName n="612">Gaius Sextius Calvinus</persName>, the consuls, made war upon the Trans alpine Gauls, and the city of the Arverni, at that time very distinguished, and their king, <persName n="78">Bituitus</persName>; and slew a vast number of men near the river Rhone. A great booty, consisting of the golden collars of the Gauls, was brought to Rome. <persName n="78">Bituitus</persName> surrendered himself to <persName n="214">Gnaeus Domitius Ahenobarbus</persName>, and was conveyed by him to Rome; and both consuls triumphed with great glory.

XXIII
In the consulship of <persName n="614">Marcus Porcius Cato</persName> and <persName n="474">Quintus Marcius Rex</persName>, in the six hundred and thirty-third year from the building of the city, a colony was led out to Narbonne in Gaul. Afterwards a triumph was obtained over Dalmatia by the consuls <persName n="281">Lucius Caecilius Metellus Delmeticus</persName> and <persName n="616">Lucius Aurelius Cotta</persName>.

XXIV
In the six hundred and thirty-fifth year from the building of the city, the consul <persName n="203">Caius Cato</persName> made war upon the Scordisci, and fought with them to his dishonour.

XXV
When <persName n="618">Gaius Caecilius Metellus Caprarius</persName> and <persName n="617">Gnaeus Papirius Carbo</persName> were consuls, <persName n="618">Gaius Caecilius Metellus Caprarius</persName> and <persName n="619">Marcus Caecilius Metellus</persName>, two brothers, had triumphs on the same day, one for Sardinia, the other for Thrace; and news was brought to Rome, that the Cimbri had crossed from Gaul into Italy.

XXVI
In the consulship of <persName n="511">Scipio Nasica</persName> and <persName n="95">Lucius Calpurnius Bestia</persName>, war was made upon <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName>, king of Numidia, because he had murdered <persName n="3">Adherbal</persName> and <persName n="232">Hiempsal</persName>, the sons of <persName n="366">Micipsa</persName>, his cousins, princes, and allies of the Roman people. The consul <persName n="95">Lucius Calpurnius Bestia</persName> being sent against him, was corrupted by the king's money, and concluded a most ignominious treaty of peace with him, which was afterwards repudiated by the senate. <persName n="620">Spurius Albinus Postumius</persName> proceeded against him in the following year: he also, through the agency of <persName n="66">Aulus Postumius</persName>, his brother, fought against the Numidians to his disgrace.

XXVII
In the third place, the consul <persName n="361">Metellus Numidicus</persName> being sent out against him, brought back the army, which he reformed with great severity and judgment, without exercising cruelty on any one, to the ancient Roman discipline. He defeated <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName> in various battles, killed or captured his elephants, and obliged many of his towns to surrender; and, when on the point of putting an end to the war, was succeeded by <persName n="602">Marius</persName>. <persName n="602">Marius</persName> overthrew both <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName> and <persName n="79">Bocchus</persName>, the king of Mauritania, who had undertaken to afford assistance to <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName>; he also took several towns in Numidia, and put an end to the war, having, through the instrumentality of his quaestor <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>, a distinguished man, taken <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName> prisoner, whom <persName n="79">Bocchus</persName>, who had before fought for him, betrayed.

In Gaul, the Cimbri were defeated by <persName n="335">Marcus Junius Silanus</persName>, the colleague of <persName n="361">Metellus Numidicus</persName>, the Scordisci and Triballi in Macedonia by <persName n="342">Marcus Minucius</persName>, and the Lusitani in Spain by <persName n="522">Servilius Caepio</persName>; and two triumphs were celebrated on account of <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName>; the first by <persName n="361">Metellus Numidicus</persName>, the second by <persName n="602">Marius</persName>. It was before the chariot of <persName n="602">Marius</persName>, however, that <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName>, with his two sons, was led in chains; and he was soon after, by order of the consul, strangled in prison.

I
While the war was going on in Numidia against <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName>, the Roman consuls, <persName n="622">Mallius</persName> and <persName n="522">Servilius Caepio</persName>, were defeated[1] by the Cimbri, Teutones, Tigurini, and Ambrones, nations of Germany and Gaul, near the river Rhone; and, being reduced by a terrible slaughter, lost their very camp, as well as the greater part of their army. Great was the consternation at Rome, such as was scarcely experienced during the Punic wars in the time of <persName n="225">Hannibal</persName>, from dread that the Gauls might again march to the city. <persName n="602">Marius</persName>, in consequence, after his victory over <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName>, was created consul the second time,[2] and the war against the Cimbri and Teutones was committed to his management. The consulship was also conferred on <persName n="602">Marius</persName> a third[3] and fourth time,[4] in consequence of the war with the Cimbri being protracted; but in his fourth consulship he had for his colleague <persName n="193">Quintus Lutatius Catulus</persName>. <persName n="602">Marius</persName> came to battle, accordingly,[5] with the Cimbri, and in two engagements killed two hundred thousand of the enemy, and took eighty thousand prisoners, with their general Teutobodus;[6] for which service he was elected consul a fifth time during his absence.[7]

II
In the meantime the Cimbri and Teutones, whose force was still innumerable, passed over into Italy. Another battle was fought with them, by <persName n="602">Marius</persName> and <persName n="193">Quintus Lutatius Catulus</persName>, though with greater success on the part of <persName n="193">Quintus Lutatius Catulus</persName>, for in that battle, in which they both commanded, a hundred and forty thousand were either slain in the field or in the pursuit, and sixty thousand taken prisoners. Of the Roman soldiers in the two armies three hundred fell. Thirty-three standards were taken from the Cimbri; of which the army of <persName n="602">Marius</persName> captured two, that of <persName n="193">Quintus Lutatius Catulus</persName> thirty-one.[8] This was the end of the war: a triumph was decreed to both the consuls.

III
In the consulship of <persName n="535">Sextus Julius Caesar</persName> and <persName n="319">Lucius Marcius Philippus</persName>, in the six hundred and fifty-ninth year from the building of the city,[9] when almost all other wars were at an end, the Piceni, Marsi, and Peligni, excited a most dangerous war in Italy;[10] for after they had lived for many years in subjection to the Roman people, they now began to assert their claim to equal privileges. This was a very destructive war. <persName n="495">Rutilius</persName>, one of the consuls, <persName n="88">Servilius Caepio</persName>, a nobleman in the flower of his age, and <persName n="432">Porcius Cato</persName>, another consul, were killed in it. The generals against the Romans on the part of the Piceni and Marsi were <persName n="596">Vettius Scaton</persName>, <persName n="230">Herius Asinius</persName>, <persName n="573">Titus Lafrenius</persName>, and <persName n="290">Lucius Cluentius</persName>. The Romans fought against them successfully under the conduct of <persName n="602">Marius</persName>, who had now been made consul for the sixth time, also under <persName n="424">Pompey Strabo</persName>, but particularly under <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>, who, among other signal exploits, so completely routed <persName n="290">Lucius Cluentius</persName>, one of the enemy's generals, with his numerous forces, that he lost only one man of his own army. The war, however, was protracted for four years, with great havoc; at length, in the fifth, it was terminated by <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> when consul, who had greatly distinguished himself on many occasions when praetor in the same war.

IV
In the six hundred and sixty-second year from the foundation of the city,[11] the first civil war began at Rome; and in the same year also the Mithridatic war. <persName n="602">Marius</persName>, when in his sixth consulship, gave rise to the Civil war; for when <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>, the consul, was sent to conduct the war against <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, who had possessed himself of Asia and Achaia, and delayed his army for a short time in Campania, in order that the remains of the Social war, of which we have just spoken, and which had been carried on within the limits of Italy, might be extinguished, <persName n="602">Marius</persName> showed himself ambitious to be appointed to the Mithridatic war. <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>, being incensed at this conduct, marched to Rome with his army. There he fought with <persName n="602">Marius</persName> and <persName n="550">Sulpicius</persName>; he was the first to enter the city in arms; <persName n="550">Sulpicius</persName> he killed; <persName n="602">Marius</persName> he put to flight; and then, having appointed <persName n="389">Octavius</persName>, and <persName n="111">Cinna</persName> the consuls for the year ensuing, set out for Asia.

V
For <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, who was king of Pontus, and possessed Armenia Minor and the entire circuit of the Pontic sea with the Bosphorus, first attempted to expel <persName n="383">Nicomedes</persName>, an ally of the Romans, from Bithynia; sending word to the senate, that he was going to make war upon him on account of the injuries which he had received. Answer was returned by the senate to <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, that if he did so he himself should feel the weight of a war from the Romans. Incensed at this reply, he immediately invaded Cappadocia, and expelled from thence <persName n="45">Ariobarzanes</persName> the king, an ally of the Roman people. He next marched into Bithynia and Paphlagonia, driving out the kings, <persName n="610">Pylaemenes</persName> and <persName n="383">Nicomedes</persName>, who were also in alliance with the Romans. He then hastened to Ephesus, and sent letters into all parts of Asia, with directions that wherever any Roman citizens should be found, they should all be put to death the same day.

VI
In the meantime Athens also, a city of Achaia, was delivered up to <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> by Aristion an Athenian. For <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> had previously sent <persName n="40">Archelaus</persName>, his general, into Achaia, with a hundred and twenty thousand horse and foot, by whom the rest of Greece was also occupied. <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> besieged <persName n="40">Archelaus</persName> at the Piraeeus near Athens, and took the city itself. Engaging afterwards in battle with <persName n="40">Archelaus</persName>, he gave him such a defeat, that out of a hundred and twenty thousand of the army of <persName n="40">Archelaus</persName> scarce ten remained; while of that of <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> only fourteen were killed. <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, on receiving intelligence of this battle, sent seventy thousand chosen troops out of Asia to <persName n="40">Archelaus</persName>, with whom <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> came again to an engagement. In the first battle twenty thousand of the enemy were slain, and <persName n="624">Diogenes</persName>, the son of <persName n="40">Archelaus</persName>; in the second the entire forces of <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> were cut off. <persName n="40">Archelaus</persName> himself lay hid for three days, stript of his armour, in the marshes. On the news of this state of things, <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> sent orders to treat with <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> concerning peace.

VII
In the meantime <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> also reduced part of the Dardanians, Scordisci, Dalmatians, and Maedians, and granted terms of alliance to the rest. But when ambassadors arrived from King <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> to treat about peace, <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> replied that he would grant it on no other condition than that he should quit the countries on which he had seized, and withdraw into his own dominions. Afterwards, however, the two came to a conference, and peace was settled between them, in order that <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>, who was in haste to proceed to the Civil war, might leave no danger in his rear; for while <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> was victorious over <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> in Achaia and Asia, <persName n="602">Marius</persName>, who had been driven from the city, and <persName n="111">Cinna</persName>, one of the consuls, had recommenced hostilities in Italy, and entering Rome, put to death the noblest of the senators and others of consular rank, proscribed many, and pulling down the house of <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> himself, forced his sons and wife to seek safety by flight; while all the rest of the senate, hastily quitting the city, fled to <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> in Greece, entreating him to come to the support of his country. He accordingly crossed over into Italy, to conduct the Civil war against the consuls <persName n="386">Norbanus</persName> and <persName n="625">Scipio Asiaticus</persName>. In the first battle he engaged with <persName n="386">Norbanus</persName> not far from Capua, when he killed seven thousand of his men, and took six thousand prisoners, losing only a hundred and twenty-four of his own army. From thence he directed his efforts against <persName n="625">Scipio Asiaticus</persName>, and before a battle was fought, or any blood shed, he received the surrender of his whole army.

VIII
But on a change of consuls at Rome, and the election of <persName n="196">Gaius Marius</persName>, the son of <persName n="602">Marius</persName>, and <persName n="100">Carbo</persName> to the consulate, <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> again came to battle with <persName n="196">Gaius Marius</persName> the younger, and killed fifteen thousand men, with the loss of only four hundred. Immediately afterwards also he entered the city. He then pursued <persName n="196">Gaius Marius</persName>, the younger, to Praeneste, besieged him there, and drove him even to self-destruction. He afterwards fought a terrible battle with Lamponius and Carinas, the leaders of the Marian faction, near the Colline gate. The number of the enemy in that battle against <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> is said to have been seventy thousand; twelve thousand surrendered themselves to <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>: the rest were cut off in the field, in the camp, or in the pursuit, by the insatiable resentment of the conqueror. <persName n="100">Carbo</persName> also, the other consul, fled from Ariminum into Sicily, and was there slain by <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>; to whom, although but a young man, being only one-and-twenty years of age, <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>, perceiving his activity, had committed the management of his troops, so that he was accounted second only to <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> himself.

IX
<persName n="100">Carbo</persName>, then, being killed, <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> recovered Sicily. Crossing next over into Africa, he put to death <persName n="778">Domitius</persName>, a leader on the side of <persName n="602">Marius</persName>, and <persName n="777">Hiarbas</persName> the king of Mauritania, who had given assistance to <persName n="778">Domitius</persName>. After these events, <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> celebrated a triumph with great pomp for his success against <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>. <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> also, while only in his twenty-fourth year, was allowed a triumph for his victories in Africa, a privilege which had been granted to no Roman before him. Such was the termination of two most lamentable wars, the Italian, also called the Social, and the Civil, which lasted for ten years, and occasioned the destruction of more than a hundred and fifty thousand men; twenty-four of consular rank, seven of praetorian, sixty of that of aedile, and nearly three hundred senators.

I
In the consulate of <persName n="6">Aemilius Lepidus</persName> and <persName n="465">Quintus Catulus</persName>,[1] after <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> had composed the troubles of the state, new wars broke out; one in Spain, another in Pamphylia and Cilicia, a third in Macedonia, a fourth in Dalmatia. <persName n="519">Sertorius</persName>, who had taken the side of <persName n="602">Marius</persName>, dreading the fate of others who had been cut off, excited the Spaniards to a war. The generals sent against him were <persName n="362">Metellus Pius</persName>, the son of that <persName n="361">Metellus Numidicus</persName> who had subdued <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName>, and the praetor <persName n="333">Marcus Domitius</persName>. <persName n="333">Marcus Domitius</persName> was killed by <persName n="236">Hirtuleius</persName>, <persName n="519">Sertorius</persName>'s general. <persName n="362">Metellus Pius</persName> contended against <persName n="519">Sertorius</persName> with various success. At length, as <persName n="362">Metellus Pius</persName> was thought singly unequal to the war, <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> was sent into Spain. Thus, two generals being opposed to him, <persName n="519">Sertorius</persName> often fought with very uncertain fortune. At last, in the eighth year of the war, he was put to death by his own soldiers, and an end made of the war by <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, at that time but a young man, and <persName n="362">Metellus Pius</persName>; and nearly the whole of Spain was brought under the dominion of the Roman people.

II
<persName n="35">Appius Claudius</persName>, on the expiration of his consulate was sent into Macedonia. He had some skirmishes with different tribes that inhabited the province of Rhodopa,[2] and there fell ill and died. <persName n="188">Gaius Scribonius Curio</persName>, on the termination of his consulship, was sent to succeed him. He conquered the Dardanians, penetrated as far as the Danube, and obtained the honour of a triumph, putting an end to the war within three years.

III
<persName n="524">Servilius Isauricus</persName>, an energetic man, was sent, after his consulate, into Cilicia and Pamphilia. He reduced Cilicia, besieged and took the most eminent cities of Lycia, amongst them Phaselis, Olympus, and Corycus. The Isauri he also attacked, and compelled to surrender, and, within three years, put an end to the war. He was the first of the Romans that marched over Mount Taurus. On his return, <persName n="524">Servilius Isauricus</persName> was granted a triumph, and acquired the surname of Isauricus.

IV
<persName n="130">Cosconius</persName> was sent into Illyricum as proconsul. He reduced a great part of Dalmatia, took Salonae, and, having made an end of the war, returned to Rome after an absence of two years.

V
About the same time, the consul <persName n="6">Aemilius Lepidus</persName>, the colleague of <persName n="465">Quintus Catulus</persName>, attempted to kindle a civil war; but in one summer that commotion was suppressed. Thus there were several triumphs at the same time, that of <persName n="362">Metellus Pius</persName> for Spain, a second for Spain obtained by <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, one of <persName n="188">Gaius Scribonius Curio</persName> for Macedonia, and one of <persName n="524">Servilius Isauricus</persName> for Isauria.

VI
In the six hundred and seventy-sixth year from the building of the city, in the consulate of <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName> and <persName n="626">Marcus Aurelius Cotta</persName>,[3] <persName n="383">Nicomedes</persName>, king of Bithynia, died, appointing by his will the Roman people his heir.

<persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, breaking the peace, again proceeded to invade Bithynia and Asia. Both the consuls being sent out against him, met with various success. <persName n="626">Marcus Aurelius Cotta</persName>, being defeated by him in a battle near Chalcedon, was even forced into the town, and besieged there. But <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, having marched from thence to Cyzicus, that, after capturing that city, he might overrun all Asia, <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName>, the other consul, met him; and, whilst <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> was detained at the siege of Cyzicus, besieged him in the rear, exhausted him with famine, defeated him in several battles, and at last pursued him to Byzantium, now called Constantinople. <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName> also vanquished his commanders in a sea-fight. Thus, in a single winter and summer, almost a hundred thousand men on the king's side were cut off by <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName>.

VII
In the six hundred and seventy-eighth year of Rome, <persName n="339">Marcus Lucullus</persName>, the cousin of that <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName> who had carried on the war against <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, obtained the province of Macedonia. A new war, too, suddenly sprung up in Italy; for eighty-four gladiators, led by <persName n="542">Spartacus</persName>, <persName n="136">Crixus</persName>, and <persName n="391">Oenomaus</persName>, having broken out of a school at Capua, made their escape; and, wandering over Italy, kindled a war in it, not much less serious than that which <persName n="225">Hannibal</persName> had raised; for, after defeating several generals and two consuls of the Romans, they collected an army of nearly sixty thousand men. They were, however, defeated in Apulia by the proconsul <persName n="133">Crassus</persName>; and, after much calamity to Italy, the war was terminated in its third year.

VIII
In the six hundred and eighty-first year from the founding of the city, in the consulate of <persName n="259">Publius Cornelius Lentulus</persName> and <persName n="627">Cnaeus Aufidius Orestes</persName>,[4] there were but two wars of any importance throughout the Roman empire, the Mithridatic and the Macedonian. Of these the two Luculli, <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName> and <persName n="339">Marcus Lucullus</persName>, had the direction. <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName>, after the battle at Cyzicus, in which he had conquered <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, and the sea-fight, in which he had overcome his generals, pursued him; and, recovering Paphlagonia and Bithynia, invaded his very kingdom. He took Sinope and Amisus, two most eminent cities of Pontus. In a second battle, near the city Cabira, where <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> had assembled a vast army from all parts of his kingdom, thirty thousand of the king's chosen troops were cut in pieces by five thousand of the Romans, and <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> was put to flight and his camp plundered. Armenia Minor, also, of which he had taken possession, was wrested from him. <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> was, however, received after his flight by <persName n="565">Tigranes</persName>, the king of Armenia, who at that time reigned in great glory; for he had frequently defeated the Persians, and had made himself master of Mesopotamia, Syria, and part of Phoenicia.

IX
<persName n="311">Lucullus</persName>, therefore, still pursuing his routed enemy, entered even the kingdom of <persName n="565">Tigranes</persName>, who ruled over both the Armenias. Tigranocerta, the most noble city of Armenia, he succeeded in taking; the king himself, who advanced against him with six hundred thousand cuirassiers, and a hundred thousand archers and other troops, he so completely defeated with a force of only eighteen thousand, that he annihilated a great part of the Armenians. Marching from thence to Nisibis, he took that city also, and made the king's brother prisoner. But as those whom <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName> had left in Pontus with part of the army in order to defend the conquered countries belonging to the Romans, grew negligent and avaricious in their conduct, they gave <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> an opportunity of again making an irruption into Pontus, and thus the war was renewed. While <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName>, after the reduction of Nisibis, was preparing for an expedition against the Persians, a successor was sent out to take his place.

X
The other <persName n="339">Marcus Lucullus</persName>, who had the management of affairs in Macedonia, was the first of the Romans that made war upon the Bessi, defeating them in a great battle on Mount Haemus; he reduced the town of Uscudama, which the Bessi inhabited, on the same day in which he attacked it; he also took Cabyle, and penetrated as far as the river Danube. He then besieged several cities lying above Pontus, where he destroyed Apollonia, Calatis, Parthenopolis, Tomi, Histros, and Burziaone,[5] and, putting an end to the war, returned to Rome. Both the Luculli, <persName n="339">Marcus Lucullus</persName> and <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName>, who ha however triumphed, but the <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName>, who had fought against <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, with the greater glory, because he had returned victorious over such powerful nations.

XI
After the Macedonian war was ended, but while that with <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> still continued (which, on the departure of <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName>, that king had renewed, collecting all his forces for the purpose), the Cretan war arose, and <persName n="360">Metellus Creticus</persName> being sent to conduct it, secured the whole province, by a succession of great battles, within three years, and received the appellation of Creticus, and a triumph on account of the island. About this time Libya also, by the will of <persName n="435">Ptolemy Apion</persName>, the king of the country, was added to the Roman empire; in it were the celebrated cities, Berenice, Ptolemais, and Cyrene.

XII
During these transactions, pirates infested all the seas, so that navigation, and that alone, was unsafe to the Romans, who were now victorious throughout the world. The war against these pirates, therefore, was committed to <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, who, with surprising success and celerity, finished it in the course of a few months. Soon after, the war against <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> and <persName n="565">Tigranes</persName> was entrusted to him; in the conduct of which, he overcame <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> in Armenia Minor in a battle by night, and plundered his camp, killing at the same time forty thousand of his troops, while he lost only twenty of his own men, and two centurions. <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> fled with his wife and two attendants; and not long after, in consequence of his cruelty to his own family, he was reduced, through a sedition excited among his soldiers by his son <persName n="407">Pharnaces</persName>, to the necessity of putting an end to his existence, and swallowed poison. Such was the end of <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, a man of singular energy and ability; his death happened near the Bosporus. He reigned sixty years, lived seventy-two, and maintained a war against the Romans for forty.

XIII
<persName n="423">Pompey</persName> next made war upon <persName n="565">Tigranes</persName>, who surrendered himself, coming to <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>'s camp at sixteen miles distance from Artaxata; and, throwing himself at his feet, pla,ced in his hands his diadem, which <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> returned to him, and treated him with great respect, but obliged him to give up part of his dominions and to pay a large sum of money: Syria, Phoenicia, and Sophene, were taken from him, and six thousand talents of silver, which he had to pay to the Roman people because he had raised a war against them without cause.

XIV
<persName n="423">Pompey</persName> soon after made war also upon the Albani;[6] and defeated their king <persName n="628">Oroeses</persName> three times; at length, being prevailed upon by letters and presents, he granted him pardon and peace. He also defeated <persName n="630">Artoces</persName>, king of Iberia,[7] in battle, and reduced him to surrender. Armenia Minor he conferred upon <persName n="147">Deiotarus</persName>, the king of Galatia, because he had acted as his ally in the Mithridatic war. To <persName n="609">Attalus</persName> and <persName n="610">Pylaemenes</persName> he restored Paphlagonia; and appointed <persName n="631">Aristarchus</persName> king of the Colchians. Shortly after he subdued the Itureans and Arabians; and, on entering Syria, rewarded Seleucia, a city near Antioch, with independence, because it had not admitted King <persName n="565">Tigranes</persName>. To the inhabitants of Antioch he restored their hostages. On those of Daphne, being charmed with the beauty of the spot and the abundance of water, he bestowed a portion of land, in order that their grove might be enlarged. Marching from thence to Judea, he took Jerusalem, the capital, in the third month; twelve thousand of the Jews being slain, and the rest allowed to surrender on terms. After these achievements, he returned into Asia, and put an end to this most tedious war.

XV
In the consulate of <persName n="607">Cicero</persName>, the orator, and <persName n="26">Antonius Hybrida</persName>, in the six hundred and eighty-ninth year from the foundation of the city, <persName n="605">Catiline</persName>, a man of very noble family, but of a most corrupt disposition, conspired to destroy his country, in conjunction with some other eminent but desperate characters. He was expelled from the city by <persName n="607">Cicero</persName>; his accomplices were apprehended and strangled in prison; and he himself was defeated and killed in battle by <persName n="26">Antonius Hybrida</persName>, the other consul.

XVI
In the six hundred and ninetieth year from the building of the city, in the consulate of <persName n="536">Silanus</persName> and <persName n="632">Murena</persName>, <persName n="360">Metellus Creticus</persName> triumphed on account of Crete, <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> for the Piratic and Mithridatic wars. No triumphal procession was ever equal to this; the sons of <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, <persName n="566">Tigranes</persName>, the son of <persName n="565">Tigranes</persName>, and <persName n="633">Aristobolus</persName>, king of the Jews, were led before his car; a vast sum of money, an immense mass of gold and silver, was carried in front. At this time there was no war of any importance throughout the world.

XVII
In the six hundred and ninety-third year from the founding of the city, <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>, who was afterwards emperor, was made consul with <persName n="75">Bibulus</persName>; and Gaul and Illyricum, with ten legions, were decreed to him. <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> first subdued the Helvetii, who are now called Sequani;[8] and afterwards, by conquering in most formidable wars, proceded as far as the British ocean. In about nine years he subdued all that part of Gaul which lies between the Alps, the river Rhone, the Rhine, and the Ocean, and extends in circumference nearly three thousand two hundred miles. <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> next made war upon the Britons, to whom not even the name of the Romans was known before his time; and having subdued them, and received hostages, sentenced them to pay a tribute. On Gaul, under the name of tribute, <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> imposed the yearly sum of forty thousand sestertia;[9] and invading the Germans on the other side of the Rhine, defeated them in several most sanguinary engagements. Among so many successes, <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> met with three defeats, once in person among the Arverni, and twice in Germany during his absence; for two of his lieutenant-generals, <persName n="570">Titurius</persName> and <persName n="131">Cotta</persName>, were cut off by ambuscades.

XVIII
About the same time, in the six hundred and ninety-seventh year from the foundation of the city, <persName n="133">Crassus</persName>, the colleague of <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> in his second consulship, was sent against the Parthians; and having engaged the enemy near Carrhae, contrary to the omens and auspices, was defeated by <persName n="551">Surena</persName>, the general of king <persName n="629">Orodes</persName>; and at last <persName n="133">Crassus</persName> was killed, together with his son <persName n="447">Publius Crassus</persName>, a most noble and excellent young man. The remains of the army were saved by <persName n="606">Cassius</persName> the quaestor, who, with singular courage, so ably retrieved the ruined fortune of the Romans, that, in his retreat over the Euphrates, he defeated the Persians in several battles.

XIX
Soon after followed the Civil war, a war truly execrable and deplorable, in which, besides the havoc that occurred in the several battles, the fortune of the Roman people was changed.[10] For <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>, on returning victorious from Gaul, proceeded to demand another consulship, and in such a manner, that it was granted him without hesitation; yet opposition was made to it by <persName n="187">Gaius Claudius Marcellus Minor</persName> the consul, <persName n="75">Bibulus</persName>, <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, and <persName n="104">Cato</persName>, and he was in consequence ordered to disband his army and return to Rome; in revenge for which insult, <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> marched with his army from Ariminum, where he kept his forces assembled, against his country. The consuls, together with <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, the whole senate, and all the nobility, fled from the city, and crossed over into Greece; and in Epirus, Macedonia, and Achaia, the senate, under <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> as their general, prepared war against <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>.

XX
<persName n="89">Caesar</persName>, having marched into the deserted city, made himself dictator. Soon after <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>, set out for Spain, where he defeated the armies of <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, which were very powerful and brave, with their three generals, <persName n="8">Afranius</persName>, <persName n="405">Petreius</persName>, and <persName n="556">Varro</persName>. Returning from thence, he went over into Greece. He took the field against <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, but in the first battle was defeated and put to flight; he escaped, however, because <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> declined to pursue him, as the night was coming on; when <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> remarked, that <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> knew not how to conquer, and that that was the only day on which he himself might have been vanquished. They next fought at Pharsalus,[11] in Thessaly, leading great forces into the field on both sides. The army of <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> consisted of forty thousand foot, six hundred horse on the left wing, and five hundred on the right, besides auxiliary troops from the whole east, and all the nobility, senators without number, men of praetorian and consular rank, and some who had already been conquerors of powerful nations. <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> had not quite thirty thousand infantry in his army, and but one thousand horse.

XXI
Never before had a greater number of Roman forces assembled in one place, or under better generals, forces which would easily have subdued the whole world, had they been led against barbarians. They fought with great eagerness, but <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> was at last overcome, and his camp plundered. <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> himself, when put to flight, sought refuge at Alexandria, with the hope of receiving aid from <persName n="440">Ptolemy XIII</persName>, the king of Egypt, to whom, on account of his youth, he had been appointed guardian by the senate; he, however, regarding fortune rather than friendship, caused <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> to be killed, and sent his head and ring to <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>; at sight of which even <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> is said to have shed tears, as he viewed the head of so great a man, once his own son-in law.

XXII
<persName n="89">Caesar</persName> soon after went to Alexandria. <persName n="440">Ptolemy XIII</persName> attempted to form a plot against his life also; for which reason war was made upon him, and, being defeated, he perished in the Nile, and his body was found covered with a golden coat of mail. <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>, having made himself master of Alexandria, conferred the kingdom on <persName n="114">Cleopatra</persName>, the sister of <persName n="440">Ptolemy XIII</persName>., with whom he himself had an illicit connexion. On his return from thence, <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> defeated in battle <persName n="407">Pharnaces</persName>, the son of <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, who had assisted <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> in Thessaly, taken up arms in Pontus, and seized upon several provinces of the Roman people; and at last drove him to self-destruction.

XXIII
Returning from thence to Rome, he created himself a third time consul with <persName n="264">Lepidus</persName>, who had been his master of the horse when dictator the year before. Next <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> went into Africa, where a great number of the nobility, in conjunction with <persName n="242">Juba</persName>, king of Mauritania, had resumed hostilities. The Roman leaders were <persName n="363">Metellus Scipio</persName>, of the most ancient family of <persName n="510">Scipio Africanus</persName> (who had also been the father-in-law of the great <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>) <persName n="405">Petreius</persName>, <persName n="589">Varus</persName>, <persName n="104">Cato</persName>, and <persName n="163">Faustus</persName>, the son of <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> the dictator. In a pitched battle fought against them, <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>, after many struggles, was victorious. <persName n="104">Cato</persName>, <persName n="363">Metellus Scipio</persName>, <persName n="405">Petreius</persName>, <persName n="242">Juba</persName>, killed themselves; <persName n="163">Faustus</persName>, <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>'s son-in-law, was slain by <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>.

XXIV
On his return to Rome the year after, <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> made himself a fourth time consul, and immediately proceeded to Spain, where the sons of <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, <persName n="221">Gnaeus Pompey</persName>, and <persName n="538">Sextus Pompey</persName>, had again raised a formidable war. Many engagements took place, the last near the city of Munda, in which <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> was so nearly defeated, that, upon his forces giving way, he felt inclined to kill himself, lest, after such great glory in war, he should fall, at the age of fifty-six, into the hands of young men. At length, having rallied his troops, he gained the victory; <persName n="221">Gnaeus Pompey, the elder son</persName> of <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, was slain, and <persName n="538">Sextus Pompey, the younger son</persName>, fled.

XXV
The civil wars throughout the world being now terminated, <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> returned to Rome, and began to conduct himself with too great arrogance, contrary to the usages of Roman liberty. As he disposed, therefore, at his own pleasure, of those honours, which were before conferred by the people and did not even rise up when the senate approached him, and exercised regal, or almost tyrannical power, in other respects, a conspiracy was formed against him by sixty or more Roman senators and knights. The chief among the conspirators were the two Bruti <persName n="81">Brutus</persName> and <persName n="144">Decimus Brutus</persName>, (of the family of that <persName n="296">Lucius Junius Brutus</persName> who had been made first consul of Rome, and who had expelled the kings) <persName n="606">Cassius</persName>, and <persName n="382">Casca</persName>. <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>, in consequence, having entered the senate house with the rest, on a certain day appointed for a meeting of the senate, was stabbed with three and twenty wounds.

I
After the assassination of <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>, in about the seven hundred and ninth year of the city, the civil wars were renewed; for the senate favoured the assassins of <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>; and <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, the consul, being of <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>'s party, endeavoured to crush them in a civil war. The state therefore being thrown into confusion, <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, perpetrating many acts of violence, was declared an enemy by the senate. The two consuls, <persName n="396">Pansa</persName> and <persName n="234">Hirtius</persName>, were sent in pursuit of him, together with <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, a youth of eighteen years of age, the nephew of <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>, [1]whom by his will he had appointed his heir, directing him to bear his name; this is the same who was afterwards called Augustus, and obtained the imperial dignity. These three generals therefore marching against <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, defeated him. It happened, however, that the two victorious consuls lost their lives; and the three armies in consequence became subject to <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> only.

II
<persName n="27">Antony</persName>, being routed, and having lost his army, fled to <persName n="264">Lepidus</persName>, who had been master of the horse to <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>, and was at that time in possession of a strong body of forces, by whom he was well received. By the mediation of <persName n="264">Lepidus</persName>, <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> shortly after made peace with <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, and, as if with intent to avenge the death of his father, by whom he had been adopted in his will, marched to Rome at the head of an army, and forcibly procured his appointment to the consulship in his twentieth year. In conjunction with <persName n="27">Antony</persName> and <persName n="264">Lepidus</persName> he proscribed the senate, and proceeded to make himself master of the state by arms. By their acts, <persName n="607">Cicero</persName> the orator, and many others of the nobility, were put to death.

III
In the meantime <persName n="81">Brutus</persName> and <persName n="606">Cassius</persName>, the assassins of <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>, raised a great war; for there were several armies in Macedonia and the East, of which they took the command. <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, therefore, and <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, proceeding against them (for <persName n="264">Lepidus</persName> remained for the defence of Italy), came to an engagement at Philippi, a city of Macedonia. In the first battle <persName n="27">Antony</persName> and <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> were defeated, but <persName n="606">Cassius</persName>, the leader of the nobility, fell; in the second they defeated and killed <persName n="81">Brutus</persName>, and very many of the nobility who had joined them in the war; and the republic was divided among the conquerors, so that <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> had Spain, the Gauls, and Italy; <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, Asia, Pontus, and the East. But the consul <persName n="277">Lucius Antonius</persName>, the brother of the <persName n="27">Antony</persName> who had fought with <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> against <persName n="81">Brutus</persName> and <persName n="606">Cassius</persName>, kindled a civil war in Italy; and being defeated near Perusia, a city of Tuscany, <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, was taken prisoner, but not put to death.

IV
In the meantime a war of a serious nature was excited in Sicily by <persName n="538">Sextus Pompey</persName>, the son of <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, those that survived of the party of <persName n="81">Brutus</persName> and <persName n="606">Cassius</persName> flocking to join him from all parts. The war against <persName n="538">Sextus Pompey</persName> was carried on by <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> and <persName n="27">Antony</persName>. A peace was at length concluded.

V
About that time <persName n="9">Agrippa</persName> met with great success in Aquitania; also <persName n="458">Publius Ventidius Bassus</persName> defeated the Persians, who were making incursions into Syria, in three engagements. He killed <persName n="634">Pacorus</persName>, the son of king <persName n="629">Orodes</persName>, on that very day on which <persName n="629">Orodes</persName>, the king of the Persians, had before put <persName n="133">Crassus</persName> to death by the hands of his general <persName n="551">Surena</persName>. He was the first who celebrated a most legitimate triumph at Rome over the Parthians.

VI
In the meantime <persName n="538">Sextus Pompey</persName> violated the peace, and, being defeated in a sea-fight, fled to Asia, and was there put to death.

<persName n="27">Antony</persName>, who was master of Asia and the East, having divorced <persName n="388">Octavia</persName>, the sister of <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, married <persName n="114">Cleopatra</persName>, queen of Egypt. He also fought in person against <persName n="629">Orodes</persName> and the Persians, and defeated them in the first encounters; but on his return suffered greatly from famine and pestilence; and as the Parthians pressed on him in his retreat, he retired from before them just as if he had been defeated.

VII
<persName n="27">Antony</persName> also excited a great civil war, at the instigation of his wife <persName n="114">Cleopatra</persName>, the queen of Egypt, who aspired with a womanish ambition to reign at Rome. He was defeated by <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> in the remarkable and celebrated sea-fight at Actium, a place in Epirus; whence he fled into Egypt, and there, as his circumstances grew desperate, since all went over to <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, committed suicide. <persName n="114">Cleopatra</persName> applied to herself an asp, and perished by its venom. Egypt was added to, the Roman empire by <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, and <persName n="635">Cnaeus Cornelius Gallus</persName> appointed governor of it; he was the first Roman judge that Egypt had.

VIII
Having thus brought wars to an end throughout the world, <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> returned to Rome in the twelfth year after he had been elected consul. From that period he held the government as sole ruler for forty-four years, for during the twelve previous years he had held it in conjunction with <persName n="27">Antony</persName> and <persName n="264">Lepidus</persName>. Thus from the beginning of his reign to the end were fifty-six years. He died a natural death in his eighty-sixth year, at the town of Atella in Campania, and his remains are interred at Rome in the Campus Martius. <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> was a man who was considered in most respects, and not without reason, to resemble a divinity, for scarcely ever was there any one more successful than he in war, or more prudent in peace. During the forty-four years that he held the government alone, <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> conducted himself with the greatest courtesy, being most liberal to all, and most faithful to his friends, whom he raised to such honours, that he placed them almost on a level with his own dignity.

IX
At no period was the Roman state more flourishing; for, to say nothing of the civil wars, in which he was unconquered, <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> added to the Roman empire Egypt, Cantabria, Dalmatia, often before conquered but only then entirely subdued, Pannonia, Aquitania, Illyricum, Rhaetia, the Vindelici and Salassi on the Alps, and all the maritime cities of Pontus, among which the two most noble were Bosporus and Panticapaeon. <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> also conquered the Dacians in battle; put to the sword numerous forces of the Germans; and drove them beyond the river Elbe, which is in the country of the barbarians far beyond the Rhine. This war however he carried on by the agency of his step-son <persName n="154">Drusus</persName>, as he had conducted the Pannonian war by that of his other step-son <persName n="563">Tiberius</persName>, in which he transplanted forty thousand prisoners from Germany, and settled them in Gaul on the bank of the Rhine. He recovered Armenia from the Parthians; the Persians gave him hostages, which they had given to no one before; and also restored the Roman standards, which they had taken from <persName n="133">Crassus</persName> when he was defeated.

X
The Scythians and Indians, to whom the Roman name was before unknown, sent him presents and ambassadors. Galatia also was made a province under his reign, having before been an independent kingdom, and <persName n="636">Marcus Lollius</persName> was the first that governed it, in quality of praetor. So much was he beloved even by the barbarians, that kings, allies of the Roman people, founded cities in his honour, to which they gave the name of Caesarea, as one in Mauritania, built by King <persName n="242">Juba</persName>, and another in Palestine, which is now a very celebrated city. Many kings, moreover, left their own dominions, and, assuming the Roman dress, that is, the toga, ran by the side of his carriage or his horse. At his death he was styled a divinity. <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> left the state in a most prosperous condition to his successor <persName n="563">Tiberius</persName>, who had been his step-son, afterwards his son-in-law, and lastly his son by adoption.

XI
<persName n="563">Tiberius</persName> distinguished his reign by great indolence, excessive cruelty, unprincipled avarice, and abandoned licentiousness. He fought on no occasion in person; the wars were carried on by his generals. Some kings, whom he induced to visit him by seducing allurements, he never sent back; among them was <persName n="623">Archelaus</persName> of Cappadocia, whose kingdom also he reduced to the form of a province, and directed that its principal city should be called after his own name; and, having been before called Mazaca, it is now termed Caesarea. He died in Campania, in the three and twentieth year of his reign, and the eighty-third of his age, to the great joy of all men.

XII
To him succeeded <persName n="637">Caligula</persName>, the grandson of <persName n="154">Drusus</persName>, the step-son of <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, and grand-nephew[2] of <persName n="563">Tiberius</persName> himself, a most wicked and cruel prince, who effaced even the memory of <persName n="563">Tiberius</persName>'s enormities. He undertook a war against the Germans; but, after entering Suevia, made no effort to do anything. He committed incest with his sisters, and acknowledged a daughter that he had by one of them. While tyrannizing over all with the utmost avarice, licentiousness, and cruelty, <persName n="637">Caligula</persName> was assassinated in the palace, in the twenty-ninth year of his age, in the third year, tenth month, and eighth day of his reign.

XIII
After him reigned <persName n="638">Claudius</persName>, the uncle of <persName n="637">Caligula</persName>, and son of that <persName n="154">Drusus</persName> who has a monument at Moguntiacum, whose grandson <persName n="637">Caligula</persName> also was. His reign was of no striking character; he acted, in many respects, with gentleness and moderation, in some with cruelty and folly. <persName n="638">Claudius</persName> made war upon Britain, which no Roman since <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> had visited; and, having reduced it through the agency of <persName n="639">Cnaeus Sentius</persName> and <persName n="640">Aulus Plautius</persName>, illustrious and noble men, he celebrated a magnificent triumph. Certain islands also, called the Orcades, situated in the ocean, beyond Britain, he added to the Roman empire, and gave his son the name of <persName n="641">Britannicus</persName>. So condescending, too, was he towards some of his friends, that he even attended <persName n="640">Aulus Plautius</persName>, a man of noble birth, who had obtained many signal successes in the expedition to Britain, in his triumph, and walked at his left hand when he went up to the Capitol. <persName n="638">Claudius</persName> lived to the age of sixty-four, and reigned fourteen years; and after his death was consecrated[3] and deified.

XIV
To him succeeded <persName n="642">Nero</persName>, who greatly resembled his uncle <persName n="637">Caligula</persName>, and both disgraced and weakened the Roman empire; he indulged in such extraordinary luxury and extravagance, that, after the example of <persName n="637">Caligula</persName>, he even bathed in hot and cold perfumes, and fished with golden nets, which he drew up with cords of purple silk. He put to death a very great number of the senate. To all good men he was an enemy. At last he exposed himself in so disgraceful a manner, that he danced and sung upon the stage in the dress of a harp-player and tragedian. He was guilty of many murders, his brother, wife, and mother, being put to death by him. He set on fire the city of Rome, that he might enjoy the sight of a spectacle such as Troy formerly presented when taken and burned.

In military affairs <persName n="642">Nero</persName> attempted nothing. Britain he almost lost; for two of its most noble towns[4] were taken and levelled to the ground under his reign. The Parthians took from him Armenia, and compelled the Roman legions to pass under the yoke. Two provinces however were formed under him; Pontus Polemoniacus, by the concession of King <persName n="643">Polemon</persName>; and the Cottian Alps, on the death of King <persName n="644">Cottius</persName>.
