<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
[57.1] [133] <persName n="509">Scipio Aemilianus</persName> besieged Numantia and restored the strictest discipline in an army that was corrupted by license and luxury.

[57.2] <persName n="509">Scipio Aemilianus</persName> forbade all tools of pleasure, expelled two thousand prostitutes from the camp, made the soldiers work every day, and ordered them to carry thirty days of food and seven stakes.

[57.3] To a man who carried it with difficulty, <persName n="509">Scipio Aemilianus</persName> said: "when you know how to make a wall from a sword, you can stop carrying the wall"; and to one who had difficulty with his shield, he said "although you are carrying a shield that is larger than prescribed, I don't blame you, because you know better how to manage a shield than to manage a sword".

[57.4] When a soldier was seen out of ranks, <persName n="509">Scipio Aemilianus</persName> had him beaten with vines when he was a Roman, or with rods if he was a foreigner.

[57.5] <persName n="509">Scipio Aemilianus</persName> sold all animals, so that they might not relieve the soldiers from their loads.

[57.6] <persName n="509">Scipio Aemilianus</persName> frequently fought successfully against enemy sallies

[57.7] When the Vaccaeans were besieged, they massacred their children and wives and killed themselves.

[57.8] Expensive presents were sent to <persName n="509">Scipio Aemilianus</persName> by king <persName n="22">Antiochus VII</persName> of Syria, and - although it was the habit of other commanders to hide royal presents - ordered to accept the gifts in front of the tribunal, and told the quaestors to enter the presents in the public accounts; from this, he would give presents to brave men.

[57.9] When <persName n="509">Scipio Aemilianus</persName> had locked up Numantia from all sides and noticed that the besieged suffered from hunger, he ordered that those enemies who went out to look for food should not be killed, because they would sooner exhaust their supplies if there were more of them.

[58.1] Against the wishes of the Senate and the equestrian order, the tribune of the plebs <persName n="564">Tiberius Gracchus</persName> carried a land bill: no one was to own more than one thousand iugera of public land. In a rage, <persName n="564">Tiberius Gracchus</persName> removed by a special enactment his colleague <persName n="343">Marcus Octavius</persName> because he had defended the opposing point of view; and he had himself, his brother <persName n="191">Gaius Gracchus</persName>, and his father-in-law <persName n="33">Appius Claudius</persName> elected as members of a triumviral board to divide land.

[58.2] He carried another land bill (aimed at getting more land) that this board was to judge which land was owned by the state and which by private individuals.

[58.3] When there turned out to be less land than he could divide without incurring the wrath of the plebeians - <persName n="564">Tiberius Gracchus</persName> had made them so greedy that they hoped for a large amount - he announced that he would promote a law to divide the money that had been bequested by king <persName n="60">Attalus III</persName> among those who would, according to his first law, have been given money.

[58.4] King <persName n="60">Attalus III</persName> of Pergamon, the son of <persName n="157">Eumenes II</persName>, had made the Roman people his heir.

[58.5] The Senate, especially former consul <persName n="571">Titus Annius</persName>, was very disturbed by these actions.

[58.6] When <persName n="571">Titus Annius</persName> had delivered a speech against <persName n="564">Tiberius Gracchus</persName> in the Senate, he was arrested by <persName n="564">Tiberius Gracchus</persName> and accused before the plebeians, and <persName n="571">Titus Annius</persName> now made a public speech against him.

[58.7] When <persName n="564">Tiberius Gracchus</persName> wanted to be reelected as tribune, he was killed on the Capitol by the optimates, led by <persName n="511">Scipio Nasica</persName>. <persName n="564">Tiberius Gracchus</persName> was first hit by a piece of a chair, and with those who perished in this fight, he was thrown in the river, without funeral.

[58.8] It also contains an account of actions with various outcomes against the Sicilian runaway slaves.

[59.1] Forced by starvation, the Numantines ran one another through and massacred themselves, and <persName n="509">Scipio Aemilianus</persName> sacked the captured city, and celebrated a triumph in the fourteenth year after the destruction of Carthage.

[59.2] [132] <persName n="454">Publius Rupilius</persName> defeated the Sicilian runaway slaves.

[59.3] <persName n="47">Aristonicus</persName>, the son of king <persName n="157">Eumenes II</persName>, occupied Asia, which had been bequested to the Roman people and was supposed to be free.

[59.4] [131] Consul <persName n="452">Publius Licinius Crassus</persName>, who was at the same time pontifex maximus (something that had never happened before), set out against him from Italy, but was defeated and killed in battle

[59.5] [130] Consul <persName n="344">Marcus Perpenna</persName>, however, accepted the surrender of the defeated <persName n="47">Aristonicus</persName>

[59.6] [129] The first two plebeian censors, <persName n="479">Quintus Pompeius</persName> and <persName n="475">Quintus Metellus</persName>, performed the lustrum ceremony.

[59.7] 318,823 citizens were registered, wards and widows not included.

[59.8] Censor <persName n="475">Quintus Metellus</persName> suggested that everyone ought to be forced to marry to create more children.

[59.9] (His speech still exists, and was quoted in the Senate by the emperor <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> as if it had recently been written, when he proposed a marriage law.)

[59.10] Tribune <persName n="179">Gaius Atinius Labeo</persName> ordered censor <persName n="475">Quintus Metellus</persName> to be thrown from the Rock, because he had not included him when he had revised the list of senators; the other tribunes assisted <persName n="475">Quintus Metellus</persName> to prevent this.

[59.11] When tribune <persName n="100">Carbo</persName> proposed that someone could be tribune as often as he wished, <persName n="509">Scipio Aemilianus</persName> argued against this law in a dignified speech, in which he said that <persName n="564">Tiberius Gracchus</persName> appeared to be lawfully killed.

[59.12] Although <persName n="191">Gaius Gracchus</persName> spoke for the proposal, <persName n="509">Scipio Aemilianus</persName> won.

[59.13] An account is given of the war between king <persName n="22">Antiochus VII</persName> of Syria and <persName n="411">Phraates II</persName> of the Parthians, and of the no less turbulent situation in Egypt.

[59.14] <persName n="438">Ptolemy VIII Euergetes</persName> was hated by his people because he was too cruel, and secretly fled to Cyprus when the people had set his palace afire; and when the kingdom was given by the people to his sister <persName n="115">Cleopatra II</persName> (whom he had divorced after he had raped and married her virgin daughter), he killed, in a fit of anger, the son she had given him, and sent the boy's head, hands, and feet to his mother.

[59.15] Riots were excited by the board of three for the division of land, <persName n="174">Fulvius Flaccus</persName>, <persName n="191">Gaius Gracchus</persName>, and <persName n="100">Carbo</persName>.

[59.16] Although he had returned home in good health, <persName n="509">Scipio Aemilianus</persName> was found dead in his bed room after he had appeared in opposition on the former day.

[59.17] His wife was suspected of poisoning him, chiefly because <persName n="515">Sempronia</persName> was the sister of <persName n="191">Gaius Gracchus</persName> and <persName n="564">Tiberius Gracchus</persName>, whom <persName n="509">Scipio Aemilianus</persName> had opposing.

[59.18] Yet there was no prosecution of the case.

[59.19] After his death, the triumviral riots were exacerbated.

[59.20] Consul <persName n="204">Gaius Sempronius</persName> at first fought unsuccessfully against the Iapydians, but the defeat was compensated by a victory won through the qualities of <persName n="145">Decimus Brutus Gallaecus</persName> (the man who had subdued Lusitania).


[60.1] [126] Consul <persName n="279">Lucius Aurelius</persName> subdued rebellious Sardinians.

[60.2] [125] <persName n="174">Fulvius Flaccus</persName>, sent out to help the Massiliots against Gallic Salluvians living on the Massilian frontier, was the first to subdue Ligurians beyond the Alps.

[60.3] Praetor <persName n="301">Lucius Opimius</persName> accepted the surrender of the rebellious Fregellans and sacked Fregellae.

[60.4] There is a reference to a plague of locusts in Africa and the large numbers of killed insects.

[60.5] [124] The censors performed the lustrum ceremony.

[60.6] 394,736 citizens were registered.

[60.7] [123] Tribune <persName n="191">Gaius Gracchus</persName>, brother of <persName n="564">Tiberius Gracchus</persName> and a better orator, carried several dangerous laws, among which was one on the supply of grain, which was to be sold for six and one-third asses to the plebs; a land bill like that of his brother; and a third law, aimed at corrupting the equestrian order (which at that time was collaborating with the Senate), that six hundred knights should be added to the Senate. Because back then, there were only three hundred senators, and the six hundred knights and three hundred senators would be mixed, the equestrian order would have a majority of two to one in the Senate.

[60.8] After <persName n="191">Gaius Gracchus</persName> had continued to a second tribuneship, he passed new land bills, which resulted in the founding of several colonies in Italy, and one in Carthage, of which he himself was one of the three founders.

[60.9] It also contains an account of the war of <persName n="358">Metellus Balearicus</persName> against those Balearans whom the Greeks call Gymnesios, because they are naked in the summer.

[60.10] The Balearans received their name from their missiles, or else from Balius, a companion of Hercules who was left behind when he sailed to Geryon.

[60.11] A description is given of the situation in Syria, in which <persName n="116">Cleopatra Thea</persName> first killed her husband <persName n="148">Demetrius II Nicator</persName> and then her son <persName n="514">Seleucus V</persName>, because she hated him. After she had killed his father, he had accepted the diadem without her permission.

From Book 61
[61.1] After he had defeated the tribe of the Salluvians, proconsul <persName n="206">Gaius Sextius</persName> founded the colony of Aquae Sextiae, which was called like this because there is much water from warm and cold springs.

[61.2] Proconsul <persName n="214">Gnaeus Domitius Ahenobarbus</persName> successfully fought against the Allobroges near the town of Vindalium.

[61.3] The reason for starting this war was that the Allobroges had offered refuge to king <persName n="577">Toutomotulus</persName> of the Salluvians, and had supported him with all possible means when he devastated the land of the Aedui, an ally of the Roman people.

[61.4] [121 BCE] After a turbulent tribuneship, <persName n="191">Gaius Gracchus</persName> occupied the Aventine with an armed mob, but, after the Senate had decided to summon the people to arms, he was routed and killed by consul <persName n="301">Lucius Opimius</persName>. Former consul <persName n="174">Fulvius Flaccus</persName>, Gracchus' ally in his madness, died with him.

[61.5] Consul <persName n="469">Quintus Fabius Maximus Allobrogicus</persName>, grandson of <persName n="276">Lucius Aemilius Paulus Macedonicus</persName>, successfully fought against the Allobroges and <persName n="78">Bituitus</persName>, the king of the Arvernians.

[61.6] From the army of <persName n="78">Bituitus</persName>, 120,000 men were killed; after the king himself had gone to Rome to make peace with the Senate, he was kept in custody at Alba, because his return to Gaul seemed not to be in the interest of tranquillity.

[61.7] It was also decided to arrest his (<persName n="78">Bituitus</persName>') son <persName n="120">Congonnetiacus</persName> and send him to Rome.

[61.8] The surrender of the Allobroges was accepted.

[61.9] [120] <persName n="301">Lucius Opimius</persName>, accused before the people by <persName n="468">Quintus Decius</persName>, tribune of the plebs, on the charge that he had sent citizens to jail without trial, was acquitted.

From Book 62
[62.1] [118] Consul <persName n="474">Quintus Marcius Rex</persName> defeated the Stynians, a nation living in the Alps.

[62.2] When he died, king <persName n="366">Micipsa</persName> of Numidia left his kingdom to his three sons <persName n="3">Adherbal</persName>, <persName n="232">Hiempsal</persName>, and <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName> (the adopted son of his brother).

[62.3] [117] <persName n="281">Lucius Caecilius Metellus Delmeticus</persName> subdued the Dalmatians.

[62.4] <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName> launched an armed attack on his brother <persName n="232">Hiempsal</persName>,

[62.5] who was defeated and killed. <persName n="3">Adherbal</persName> was expelled from the kingdom, but restored by the Senate.

[62.6] <persName n="281">Lucius Caecilius Metellus Delmeticus</persName> and <persName n="214">Gnaeus Domitius Ahenobarbus</persName>, acting as censors, removed thirty-two members from the Senate.

[62.7] It also contains an account of disturbances in Syria and a quarrel between its kings.

Book 63
[63.1] [114] In Thrace, consul <persName n="203">Gaius Porcius</persName> unsuccessfully fought against the Scordiscians.

[63.2] The censors performed the lustrum ceremony.

[63.3] 394,336 citizens were registered.

[63.4] The Vestal virgins <persName n="4">Aemilia</persName>, <persName n="266">Licinia</persName>, and <persName n="318">Marcia</persName> were condemned for unchastity. There is a description of how this unchastity was committed, discovered, and punished.

[63.5] [113] In pursuit of plunder, the nomadic tribe of the Cimbrians came to Illyricum.

[63.6] Consul <persName n="100">Carbo</persName> and his army were defeated by them.

[63.7] [112] In Thrace, consul <persName n="269">Livius Drusus</persName> successfully fought against the Scordiscians, a nation of Gallic descent.

From Book 64
[64.1] <persName n="3">Adherbal</persName>, attacked by <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName> and besieged in the town of Cirtha was killed in violation of a senatorial decree. [111] Because of this, war was declared upon <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName>, and consul <persName n="95">Calpurnius Bestia</persName>, who was sent out to conduct this war, concluded a treaty with <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName>, without being ordered to do so by the people or the Senate.

[64.2] Under safe-conduct, <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName> was invited to Rome so that he might indicate the instigators of his plots (he was said to have corrupted many senators with bribes), and arrived. Because he killed some sort of king who was called <persName n="351">Massiva</persName> and tried to claim the kingdom of the hated <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName> from the Roman people, <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName> risked standing trial for his life, and secretly fled. It is said that when he left the city, he commented: "What a corrupt city! It will perish as soon as it finds someone to buy it."

[64.3] [110] Deputy <persName n="66">Aulus Postumius</persName> was defeated in battle by <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName> and added to this an dishonorable peace treaty, which the Senate preferred not to ratify.

From Book 65
[65.1] [109] Consul <persName n="361">Metellus Numidicus</persName> defeated <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName> in two battles and devastated all Numidia.

[65.2] [108] Consul <persName n="335">Marcus Junius Silanus</persName> unsuccessfully fought against the Cimbrians.

[65.3] The Senate ignored the envoys of the Cimbrians who demanded land and a place to settle.

[65.4] Proconsul <persName n="342">Marcus Minucius</persName> successfully fought against the Thracians.

[65.5] [107] In the country of the Nitiobriges, consul <persName n="287">Lucius Cassius</persName> was massacred with his army by the Gallic Tigurini, a Helvetian tribe that had left its own country.

[65.6] After the soldiers who had survived the disaster had given hostages and half of their possessions, they arranged to be released unharmed.

From Book 66
[66.1] [106 BCE] When <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName>, expelled from Numidia by <persName n="602">Marius</persName>, received help of <persName n="79">Bocchus</persName>, king of the Maurians, <persName n="79">Bocchus</persName>' troops were slaughtered in battle and <persName n="79">Bocchus</persName> no longer wanted to continue the war he had so unfortunately undertaken. He threw <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName> in chains and handed him over to <persName n="602">Marius</persName>; in this affair, the main actor was <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>, the quaestor of <persName n="602">Marius</persName>.

From Book 67
[67.1] [105] After the defeat of his army, <persName n="326">Marcus Aurelius Scaurus</persName>, a deputy of the consul, was captured by the Cimbrians and called to their council, where he deterred them from crossing the Alps and going to Italy, saying that the Romans were unconquerable. He was killed by a savage young man, <persName n="80">Boiorix</persName>.

[67.2] Defeated by the same enemies, consul <persName n="219">Gnaeus Manlius</persName> and proconsul <persName n="522">Caepio</persName> were stripped of both their camps; according to <persName n="582">Valerius Antias</persName>, 80,000 soldiers and 40,000 servants and camp followers were killed near Arausio.

[67.3] <persName n="522">Caepio</persName>, who had caused the defeat by his rashness, was convicted; his possessions were confiscated (for the first time since <persName n="552">Tarquinius Superbus</persName>) and his powers abrogated.

[67.4] [104] During the triumph of <persName n="602">Marius</persName>, <persName n="244">Jugurtha</persName> walked in front of the chariot with his two sons, and was killed in the jail.

[67.5] <persName n="602">Marius</persName> entered the Senate in triumphal dress, something no one had ever done before, and his consulship was prolonged out of fear of the Cimbrian war.

[67.6] <persName n="602">Marius</persName> was away when he was elected for consul for the second and third time, and obtained a fourth consulship by pretending not to be aiming for it.

[67.7] The people chose <persName n="214">Gnaeus Domitius Ahenobarbus</persName> as pontifex maximus.

[67.8] Having devastated everything between Rhône and Pyrenees, the Cimbrians moved through a mountain pass into Hispania, where they were - after having devastated many districts - routed by the Celtiberians. They returned to Gaul and joined the Teutons in the land of the Veliocassians.

From Book 68
[68.1] Praetor <persName n="323">Marcus Antonius Creticus</persName> pursued the pirates to Cilicia.

[68.2] [102] Consul <persName n="602">Marius</persName> defended his camp against a violent attack by the Teutons and Ambronians.

[68.3] After this, he defeated these enemies in two battles near Aquae Sextiae, in which - they say - 200,000 enemies were killed and 90,000 captured.

[68.4] [101] Although away from home, <persName n="602">Marius</persName> was elected consul for the fifth time.

[68.5] He postponed the triumph offered to him until he had also defeated the Cimbrians.

[68.6] The Cimbrians, who had driven back and put to flight proconsul <persName n="193">Quintus Catulus</persName>, who had wanted to block the passes in the Alps (near the river Adige he left a cohort that occupied a mountain castle; but by its own valour it broke away and followed the fleeing proconsul and his army), invaded Italy, [100] but were defeated in battle by the united forces of this <persName n="193">Quintus Catulus</persName> and <persName n="602">Marius</persName>; it is said that 160,000 enemies were killed and 60,000 captured.

[68.7] Although <persName n="602">Marius</persName>, welcomed by the applause of the entire state, had been offered two triumphs, he was content with one.

[68.8] The first men in the state, who had until then envied the "new man" who had reached so many important posts, now admitted that the state had been rescued by him.

[68.9] <persName n="441">Publicius Malleolus</persName>, who had killed his mother, was the first to be sewn into a sack and thrown into the sea.

[68.10] It is said that the sacred shields moved and rattled before the Cimbrian war was over.

[68.11] It also contains an account of a war between the Syrian kings.

From Book 69
[69.1] Using violence, <persName n="503">Saturninus</persName>, who had the support of <persName n="602">Marius</persName>, and whose rival <persName n="64">Aulus Nunnius</persName> had been killed by soldiers, was made tribune of the plebs, and occupied his tribuneship no less violently than he had tried to obtain it. When he had, using violence, passed a land bill, he accused <persName n="361">Metellus Numidicus</persName>, who had not sworn to uphold this law.

[69.2] <persName n="361">Metellus Numidicus</persName> was defended by the better citizens, but went into voluntary exile at Rhodes because he refused to be the cause of civil struggle. Here, he found distraction in reading and listening to great orators.

[69.3] When <persName n="361">Metellus Numidicus</persName> had left, <persName n="602">Marius</persName>, who was responsible for the riot and had bought a sixth consulship by distributing money to the voting districts, confirmed <persName n="361">Metellus Numidicus</persName>' exile.

[69.4] The same tribune <persName n="503">Saturninus</persName> assassinated <persName n="354">Memmius</persName>, a candidate for the consulship whom he feared to be against him.

[69.5] Shocked by these crimes, the Senate, to whose side <persName n="602">Marius</persName> (a man of constantly changing ideas and plans, always following fortune) had gone over, put <persName n="503">Saturninus</persName> down, together with the praetor <persName n="212">Glaucia</persName>  and other allies who accompanied him in his madness, and had him killed in something like a battle.

[69.6] With the approval of the entire community, <persName n="361">Metellus Numidicus</persName> was recalled from exile.

[69.7] Proconsul <persName n="315">Manius Aquilius</persName> put an end to the war against the slaves that had originated in Sicily.

From Book 70
[70.1] When <persName n="315">Manius Aquilius</persName> was accused of extortion, he refused to appeal to the jury, and <persName n="322">Marcus Antonius</persName>, who had spoken for him, tore the tunic from his chest to show his honorable scars.

[70.2] Without further ado, he was acquitted.

[70.3] (<persName n="607">Cicero</persName> is the only source for this case.)

[70.4] [97] Proconsul <persName n="572">Titus Didius</persName> successfully fought against the Celtiberians.

[70.5] [96] After his death, king <persName n="435">Ptolemy Apion</persName> of Cyrene, surnamed Apion, made the Roman people his inheritor and the Senate decreed that all the towns in his kingdom were to be free.

[70.6] [95] <persName n="45">Ariobarzanes I</persName> of Cappadocia was brought back to the kingdom of Cappadocia by <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>.

[70.7] Envoys of the Parthians, sent by <persName n="372">Mithradates II</persName>, came to <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> to ask for the friendship of the Roman people.

[70.8] [92] Because as deputy of governor <persName n="198">Gaius Mucius</persName> he had defended Asia against the injustice of the publicans, <persName n="496">Rutilius</persName>, a man of supreme innocence, was hated by the equestrian order, which controlled the law courts and sent him into exile because of extortion.

[70.9] Praetor <persName n="205">Gaius Sentius</persName> unsuccessfully fought against the Thracians.

[70.10] [91] The Senate, which refused to accept the control of the law courts by the equestrian order, started to try to transfer control to the Senate itself. It was supported by tribune <persName n="269">Livius Drusus</persName>, who, to obtain more power, stirred up the people with the dangerous hope of a largesse.

[70.11] It also contains an account of the troubles in the Syrian kingdom.

From Book 71
[71.1] [91 BCE] <persName n="269">Livius Drusus</persName>, a tribune of the plebs who wanted to reinforce the powers of the Senate, appealed to the allies and Italian nations and made them hope for the Roman citizenship; with their help, he carried by force laws on the distribution of land and grain, and also carried a law on jurisdiction to the effect that the juries would be made up from one half of senators and one half of knights.

[71.2] When he could not keep his promise to give citizenship to his allies, the angry Italians started to think about defection.

[71.3] Their gatherings and conspiracies and the speeches in the council of their leaders are reported.

[71.4] For these reasons, <persName n="269">Livius Drusus</persName> became hated even in the Senate, as if he had been the cause of the Social War, and he was assassinated by an unknown person in his own house.

From Book 72
[72.1] The following Italian nations revolted: the Picentes, Vestinians, Marsians, Paelignians, Marrucinians, Samnites, and Lucanians.

[72.2] The first act of war was by the Picentes, who killed proconsul <persName n="481">Quintus Servilius</persName> in the town Asculum, with all Roman citizens who were in this town.

[72.3] The people put on the war dress.

[72.4] <persName n="525">Servius Galba</persName>, who was captured by the Lucanians, was released from captivity by one single woman, with whom he had been lodging.

[72.5] The colonies of Aesernia and Alba were besieged by the Italians.

[72.6] The troops sent to the relief of the Roman people by the Latins and foreign nations, the expeditions from both sides, and the storming of cities are also described.

From Book 73
[73.1] [90] <persName n="295">Lucius Julius Caesar</persName>, the consul, lost a battle against the Samnites.

[73.2] The colonia at Nola fell in the hands of the Samnites, together with praetor <persName n="305">Lucius Postumus</persName>, who was executed by them.

[73.3] Many nations sided with the enemies.

[73.4] When consul <persName n="495">Rutilius</persName> had fought against the Marsians, with mixed results, and had fallen in battle, his deputy <persName n="602">Marius</persName> had more success in a battle against the enemy.

[73.5] <persName n="550">Sulpicius</persName> routed the Paelignians.

[73.6] When <persName n="88">Caepio</persName>, deputy of <persName n="495">Rutilius</persName>, was besieged and successfully repelled his enemies, and was given equal powers to <persName n="602">Marius</persName>, he became reckless, was trapped in an ambush, and fell in the rout of his army.

[73.7] Consul <persName n="295">Lucius Julius Caesar</persName> fought successfully against the Samnites.

[73.8] Because of his victory, at Rome, the battle dress was laid aside.

[73.9] To show the varying fortunes of war, the colony at Aeserna, together with <persName n="588">Marcus Marcellus</persName>, fell in the hands of the Samnites, but <persName n="602">Marius</persName> routed the Marsians, and <persName n="230">Hierius Asinius</persName>, the commander of the Marrucinians, was killed.

[73.10] In Transalpine Gaul, <persName n="181">Gaius Caelius</persName> defeated the rebellious Salluvians.

From Book 74
[74.1] [89] <persName n="424">Pompey Strabo</persName> routed [and?] besieged the Picentes.

[74.2] Because of this victory, the purple-bordered togas and other distinctions of the magistrates were assumed.

[74.3] <persName n="602">Marius</persName> fought against the Marsians, with an unclear outcome.

[74.4] For the first time, freedmen were allowed to serve in the army.

[74.5] Deputy <persName n="65">Aulus Plotius</persName> defeated the Umbrians and praetor <persName n="304">Lucius Porcius</persName> the Etruscans. Both nations had revolted.

[74.6] In Bithynia <persName n="383">Nicomedes</persName> was restored to the throne and <persName n="45">Ariobarzanes I</persName> of Cappadocia in the kingdom of Cappadocia.

[74.7] [88] Consul <persName n="424">Pompey Strabo</persName> defeated the Marsians in an open battle.

[74.8] Because the citizenry was oppressed by debts, praetor <persName n="54">Asellio</persName>, who was deciding cases in favor of the debtors, was killed in the Forum by usurers.

[74.9] It also contains an account of Thracian raids into Macedonia.

From Book 75
[75.1] The deputy <persName n="66">Aulus Postumius</persName>, commander of the navy, was killed by his own army because he was suspected of the infamous crime of high treason.

[75.2] Deputy <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> defeated the Samnites in battle and expelled them from two of their camps.

[75.3] <persName n="424">Pompey Strabo</persName> accepted the surrender of the Vestinians.

[75.4] After a successful campaign and repeatedly routing the Marsians, consul <persName n="304">Lucius Porcius</persName> fell while storming one of their camps.

[75.5] This event gave the victory in that battle to the enemies.

[75.6] <persName n="130">Cosconius</persName> and <persName n="270">Lucanus</persName> defeated the Samnites in battle, killing <persName n="348">Marius Egnatius</persName>, the most noble leader of their enemies. They accepted the surrender of several towns.

[75.7] <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> subdued the Hirpinians, defeated the Samnites in several battles, accepted the surrender of a number of people, and proceeded to Rome to run for consul, having achieved more than most people achieve before their consulship.

From Book 76
[76.1] [89 BCE] Deputy <persName n="63">Aulus Gabinius</persName> had successfully waged war against the Lucanians and had captured many towns, when he was killed during the siege of a camp.

[76.2] Commander <persName n="550">Sulpicius</persName> slaughtered all Marrucinians and accepted the surrender of the entire region.

[76.3] Proconsul <persName n="424">Pompey Strabo</persName> accepted the surrender of the Vestinians and Paelignians.

[76.4] The Marsians, broken in several battles by the deputies <persName n="111">Cinna</persName> and <persName n="362">Metellus Pius</persName>, started to beg for peace.

[76.5] <persName n="424">Pompey Strabo</persName> captured Asculum.

[76.6] After the Italians had been defeated again by deputy <persName n="7">Aemilius Mamercus</persName>, the leader of the Marsians and ringleader of the affair, <persName n="430">Poppaedius Silo</persName>, fell in battle.

[76.7] [88] <persName n="45">Ariobarzanes I</persName> of Cappadocia and <persName n="383">Nicomedes</persName> of Bithynia were dethroned by <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, king of Pontus.

[76.8] It also contains an account of raids and plundering by the Thracians in Macedonia.

From Book 77
[77.1] When tribune of the plebs <persName n="550">Sulpicius</persName>, on the instigation of <persName n="602">Marius</persName>, had proposed dangerous laws (that the exiles would be recalled, new citizens and freedmen would be divided in voting districts, and <persName n="602">Marius</persName> would be appointed leader against <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, king of Pontus), and had used violence against the opposing consuls <persName n="478">Quintus Pompeius</persName> and <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>, killing <persName n="421">Pompeius</persName> (the son of consul <persName n="478">Quintus Pompeius</persName> and son-in-law of <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>), <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> entered the city with an army, fought a battle against the factions of <persName n="550">Sulpicius</persName> and <persName n="602">Marius</persName> in the city itself, and expelled them.

[77.2] Twelve members of this faction - among others father <persName n="602">Marius</persName> and son <persName n="196">Gaius Marius</persName> - were proclaimed enemies by the Senate.

[77.3] When <persName n="550">Sulpicius</persName> was hiding in a villa, he was hunted down and killed on information given by his own slave.

[77.4] Because he had shown the way, the slave received the promised freedom, but was thrown from the Rock because of his criminal betrayal of his master.

[77.5] The younger <persName n="196">Gaius Marius</persName> crossed to Africa.

[77.6] The elder <persName n="602">Marius</persName> hid himself in the marches near Minturnae, but was dragged out by the citizens. When a slave from Gaul was sent out to kill him, he withdrew because he feared the greatness of this man, and <persName n="602">Marius</persName> was put on one of the town's ships and sent to Africa.

[77.7] <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> reordered the state and sent out colonies.

[77.8] Consul <persName n="478">Quintus Pompeius</persName> set out to take over the army of proconsul <persName n="424">Pompey Strabo</persName>, but was killed by the latter.

[77.9] King <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> of Pontus, having occupied Bithynia and Cappadocia and having expelled governor <persName n="315">Manius Aquilius</persName>, invaded Phrygia, a province of the Roman people, with an enormous army.

From Book 78
[78.1] <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> occupied Asia, cast into chains proconsul <persName n="477">Quintus Oppius</persName>, did the same to his deputy <persName n="315">Manius Aquilius</persName>, and on <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>' command all Roman citizens in Asia were killed in one single day.

[78.2] He attacked the city of Rhodes, which alone had remained faithful to the Roman people, but was defeated in several naval battles, and retired.

[78.3] <persName n="40">Archelaus</persName>, the deputy of the king, went to Greece with an army and occupied Athens.

[78.4] It also contains an account of the disorders in the cities and on the islands, as some wanted to side with <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, and others with the Roman people.

From Book 79
[79.1] [87] When consul <persName n="111">Cinna</persName> was carrying dangerous laws by violence and arms, he along with six tribunes of the plebs was expelled from the city by his colleague <persName n="389">Octavius</persName> and deprived of his office, but with bribes, he brought the army of <persName n="34">Appius Claudius</persName> in his power and carried the war into the city, recalling <persName n="196">Gaius Marius</persName> and other exiles from Africa.

[79.2] (In this war, two brothers, one from the army of <persName n="424">Pompey Strabo</persName> and one from <persName n="111">Cinna</persName>'s, unknowingly engaged, and when the winner was stripping the man he had killed, he cried heavily when he recognized his brother and built a pyre, on which he stabbed himself, and was consumed by the same fire.)

[79.3] And although [the civil war] could have been suppressed at the very beginning, by the treason of  <persName n="424">Pompey Strabo</persName> (who supported both sides and did not bring help to the optimates till their position had become desperate) and by the slowness of the consul, the position of <persName n="111">Cinna</persName> and <persName n="602">Marius</persName> was strengthened, so that they were able to besiege the city with four armies, two of which were given to <persName n="519">Sertorius</persName> and <persName n="100">Carbo</persName>.

[79.4] <persName n="602">Marius</persName> captured the colony at Ostia and sacked it cruelly.

From Book 80
[80.1] Citizenship was given to the Italian nations by the Senate.

[80.2] The Samnites, the only ones to take up arms again, sided with <persName n="111">Cinna</persName> and <persName n="602">Marius</persName>.

[80.3] They defeated deputy <persName n="416">Plautius</persName> and his army.

[80.4] <persName n="111">Cinna</persName> and <persName n="602">Marius</persName>, together with <persName n="100">Carbo</persName> and <persName n="519">Sertorius</persName>, attacked the Janiculum, but were routed by consul <persName n="389">Octavius</persName> and retreated.

[80.5] <persName n="602">Marius</persName> captured the colonies at Antium and Aricia and Lanuvium.

[80.6] When, because of the slowness and perfidy of both their leaders and their soldiers (who were bribed and did not want to fight or moved to other regions), the optimates had lost all hope of holding out, <persName n="111">Cinna</persName> and <persName n="602">Marius</persName> were received in the city, which they treated with murder and rape as if it were conquered. Consul <persName n="389">Octavius</persName> was killed and all noble members of the opposite party butchered, like <persName n="322">Marcus Antonius</persName> (a man of great eloquence), and <persName n="192">Gaius Julius Caesar Strabo</persName> and <persName n="295">Lucius Julius Caesar</persName>, whose heads were placed on the speaker's platform

[80.7] The younger <persName n="134">Crassus</persName> was killed by the knights of <persName n="167">Fimbria</persName>, and the elder <persName n="267">Licinius Crassus</persName>, wishing to avoid a fate unworthy of his dignity, stabbed himself with his sword.

[80.8] And without even the appearance of election, they [<persName n="111">Cinna</persName> and <persName n="602">Marius</persName>] appointed themselves consuls for the next year.

[80.9] [86] On the very day of the beginning of his magistracy, <persName n="602">Marius</persName> ordered that the senator <persName n="532">Sextus Licinius</persName> was to be thrown from the rock. After many crimes, <persName n="602">Marius</persName> died on the Ides of January. When we take everything into account, he had been a man about whom it was not easy to say whether he was more excellent in times of war than he was dangerous in times of peace.

[80.10] It can therefore be said that as much as he saved the state as a soldier, so much he damaged it as a citizen - first by his tricks, later by his revolutionary actions.

[81.1] [87 BCE] <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> besieged Athens, which had been occupied by <persName n="40">Archelaus</persName>, an officer of <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>;

[81.2] [86] after much labor he took the city, and he gave it back the freedom it used to have.

[81.3] Magnesia, the only city in Asia that remained loyal, was defended against <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> with the greatest courage.

[81.4] It also contains an account of Thracian raids into Macedonia.

From Book 82
[82.1] <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> defeated in battle the army of the king, which had occupied Macedonia and entered Thessaly. 100,000 enemies were killed and the camp was captured.

[82.2] Later, the war was renewed and <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> defeated and destroyed a second army of the king.

[82.3] <persName n="40">Archelaus</persName> and the royal navy surrendered to <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>.

[82.4] Because of his avarice, consul <persName n="583">Valerius Flaccus</persName>, the colleague of <persName n="111">Cinna</persName>, who was sent out to replace <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>, was impopular with his army, and he was murdered by his own deputy, <persName n="167">Fimbria</persName>, an utterly reckless man, and the command was transferred to <persName n="167">Fimbria</persName>.

[82.5] It also contains accounts of <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>' attack on the cities in Asia, the ruin of that province, and Thracian raids into Macedonia.

From Book 83
[83.1] After defeating in Asia several commanders of <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> in battle, <persName n="167">Fimbria</persName> captured the city of Pergamon, and narrowly failed to arrest the king he was besieging.

[83.2] He also took and sacked the city of Troy, which was waiting to surrender to <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>, and recovered a large part of Asia.

[83.3] <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> crushed the Thracians in many battles.

[83.4] [85] When <persName n="111">Cinna</persName> and <persName n="100">Carbo</persName>, who had made themselves consuls for two years, were preparing the war against <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>, <persName n="584">Valerius Flaccus</persName> (the princeps of the Senate) delivered a speech in the Senate and, with the help of those who were pressing for unity, made sure that envoys were sent to <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> to discuss peace.

[83.5] [84] <persName n="111">Cinna</persName> was killed by his own army, which he had tried to force against its will to board ships and set out against <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>.

[83.6] <persName n="100">Carbo</persName> was now sole consul.

[83.7] [85] <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> crossed into Asia and made peace with <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, so that he ceded the provinces of Asia, Bithynia, and Cappadocia.

[83.8] <persName n="167">Fimbria</persName>, left by his army, which sided with <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>, stabbed himself, offered his neck to a slave, and persuaded the latter to kill him.

From Book 84
[84.1] <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> replied to the envoys who had been sent by the Senate that he would submit to the authority of the Senate if the rights of the citizens who had been expelled by <persName n="111">Cinna</persName> and fled to him, were restored.

[84.2] Although this demand appeared to be reasonable to the Senate, <persName n="100">Carbo</persName> and his faction, to whom war seemed more useful, prevented an agreement.

[84.3] When the same <persName n="100">Carbo</persName> wanted to ask for hostages from all Italian towns and colonies, to secure their loyalty against <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>, this was prevented by a unified Senate.

[84.4] By senatorial decree, the new citizens received the right to vote.

[84.5] After <persName n="362">Metellus Pius</persName>, who had embraced the politics of the optimates and provoked a war in Africa, had been defeated by praetor <persName n="189">Gaius Fabius</persName>, the faction of <persName n="100">Carbo</persName> and the adherents of <persName n="602">Marius</persName> passed a senatorial decree that all armies everywhere ought to be disbanded.

[84.6] Freedmen were registered in the thirty-five voting districts.

[84.7] It also contains an account of the preparations of the war that was to be launched against <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>.

From Book 85
[85.1] [83] When <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> crossed into Italy with his army, he sent envoys to talk about peace, but when they were maltreated by consul Norbanus, he defeated this same Norbanus in battle.

[85.2] And when he was about to attack the camp of <persName n="307">Lucius Scipio</persName> (the other consul), with whom he had unsuccessfully tried to reach an agreement, the entire consular army, invited by soldiers sent by <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>, transferred its allegiance to <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>.

[85.3] <persName n="307">Lucius Scipio</persName>, who might have been killed, was released.

[85.4] <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> (the son of the <persName n="424">Pompey Strabo</persName> who had captured Asculum) conscripted a three-legion army of volunteers and went to <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>, to whom all leading men of Rome made their way as well, and because of this going to the camp, the city seemed abandoned.

[85.5] It also contains an account of the expeditions of war leaders of both sides all over Italy.

From Book 86
[86.1] [83 BCE] After <persName n="196">Gaius Marius</persName>, son of <persName n="602">Marius</persName>, had, by the use of violence, been made consul before he was twenty years old, <persName n="189">Gaius Fabius</persName> was burned alive in his headquarters in Africa because of his cruelty and avarice.

[86.2] <persName n="302">Lucius Philippus</persName>, a deputy of <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>, occupied Sardinia after having expelled and killed praetor <persName n="462">Quintus Antonius</persName>.

[86.3] <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> concluded a treaty with the Italian nations, which prevented him from being regarded as a threat to their recently obtained citizenship and voting rights.

[86.4] And because he now had become confident about his victory, he ordered people who wanted him to judge cases to deposit their bonds at Rome, even though the city was still kept by his enemies.

[86.5] [82] At the wish of consul <persName n="196">Gaius Marius</persName>, praetor <persName n="141">Damasippus</persName> convened the Senate and massacred every man belonging to the nobility living in Rome.

[86.6] Among his victims was <persName n="666">Mucius Scaevola</persName>, who was murdered at the entrance of the shrine of Vesta.

[86.7] It also contains an account of the renewal of the war against <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> in Asia.

From Book 87
[87.1] After routing and destroying his army at Sacriportus, <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> besieged <persName n="196">Gaius Marius</persName> in the town of Praeneste, and recovered the city of Rome from the hands of his enemies.

[87.2] He repelled <persName n="196">Gaius Marius</persName> when he tried to break away.

[87.3] It also contains accounts of the achievements of his deputies, who obtained the same happy results.

From Book 88
[88.1] <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> drove <persName n="100">Carbo</persName> out of Italy, having defeated his army at Clusium, Faventia, and Fidentia, and fought, with the Samnites (the only Italian nation that had not laid down its weapons yet) near the city of Rome at the Porta Collina, and having restored the state, soiled his beautiful victory with a greater cruelty than anyone had ever displayed.

[88.2] In the Villa publica, he killed 8,000 people who had already surrendered, set up a proscription list, filled the city and all of Italy with slaughter, ordered the murder of all unarmed Praenestines, and killed xxxx, a man of senatorial rank, after having broken his legs and arms, cutting off his ears and pulling out his eyes.

[88.3] When <persName n="196">Gaius Marius</persName>, still besieged at Praeneste by <persName n="392">Ofella</persName> of the Sullan faction, wanted to escape through a tunnel that turned out to be blocked by the army, he choose death.

[88.4] That means that when he found out that there was no escape from the tunnel, he and <persName n="555">Telesinus</persName>, his companion in flight, ran into each other's drawn swords; <persName n="602">Marius</persName> killed the other, was wounded himself, and killed by his slave.

From Book 89
[89.1] <persName n="82">Brutus</persName>, sent in a fisherman's ship by <persName n="100">Carbo</persName> from Cossyra, where they had put in, to Lilybaeum, to see if <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> was already there, was surrounded by ships sent by <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>; he pointed his sword against himself and bracing it on a thwart of the ship, fell upon it with all his weight.

[89.2] [81] <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, sent to Sicily by the Senate with special powers, killed <persName n="100">Carbo</persName>, who met his death crying like a woman.

[89.3] <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> was made dictator, and had twenty-four fasces carried before him, something that no one had ever done before.

[89.4] With new laws, he strengthened the republic, diminished the powers of the tribunes of the plebs by taking away from them the right to introduce legislation, expanded the number of priests and augurs to fifteen, enrolled members of the equestrian order into the Senate, blocked the children of those who were proscribed from obtaining office, sold their possessions, and was the first to seize the profits.

[89.5] The proceeds were 350,000,000 sesterces.

[89.6] He had <persName n="392">Ofella</persName> murdered at the Forum because he had run for consul against his wishes, convened a meeting and explained to the angry Roman people that he had ordered the assassination.

[89.7] In Africa, <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> defeated and killed the exiled <persName n="213">Ahenobarbus</persName> and king <persName n="233">Hierta</persName> of Numidia (who were stirring up war), and at the age of twenty-four, celebrated his African triumph, even though he was still a Roman knight - an honor without precedent.

[89.8] When Norbanus, an exiled former consul, was arrested in the city of Rhodes, he committed suicide.

[89.9] Another exiled man, <persName n="380">Mutilus</persName>, secretly, with his head covered, arrived at the rear entrance of his wife <persName n="284">Bastia</persName>'s residence, but was not allowed to enter because he had been proscribed.

[89.10] Consequently, he stabbed himself and besprinkled the doorway of his wife with his blood.

[89.11] <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> recaptured Nola in Samnium.

[89.12] He settled forty-seven legions in the conquered country and divided it between them.

[89.13] He besieged Volaterrae, a town still putting up resistance, and accepted its surrender.

[89.14] Finally, Mytilene in Asia, the only city still in arms after the defeat of <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, was captured and destroyed.

From Book 90
[90.1] [78] <persName n="549">Sulla</persName> died and the Senate honored him by allowing his burial on the Campus Martius.

[90.2] <persName n="6">Aemilius Lepidus</persName>, who tried to revoke the acts of <persName n="549">Sulla</persName>, caused a war.

[90.3] He was expelled form Italy by his colleague <persName n="465">Quintus Catulus</persName> and died in Sardinia, where he had, in vain, tried to stir up a war.

[90.4] <persName n="328">Marcus Brutus</persName>, who had received Cisalpine Gaul, was killed by <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>.

[90.5] <persName n="519">Sertorius</persName>, another exile, launched a very big war in Hispania Ulterior.

[90.6] Proconsul <persName n="298">Lucius Manlius</persName> and <persName n="333">Marcus Domitius</persName>, his deputy, were defeated in battle by quaestor <persName n="236">Hirtuleius</persName>.

[90.7] It also contains an account of the war waged by proconsul <persName n="524">Servilius Isauricus</persName> against the Cilicians.

From Book 91
[91.1] [77 BCE] Although <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> was still a Roman knight, he was sent out against <persName n="519">Sertorius</persName> with the powers of a proconsul.

[91.2] <persName n="519">Sertorius</persName> stormed several cities and subdued several tribes.

[91.3] Proconsul <persName n="35">Appius Claudius</persName> defeated the Thracians in several battles.

[91.4] Proconsul <persName n="362">Metellus Pius</persName> defeated <persName n="236">Hirtuleius</persName>, a quaestor of <persName n="519">Sertorius</persName>, and his army.

From Book 92
[92.1] [76] <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> fought against <persName n="519">Sertorius</persName> a battle with an unclear outcome, because on both sides one wing was victorious.

[92.2] <persName n="362">Metellus Pius</persName> defeated <persName n="519">Sertorius</persName> and <persName n="403">Perpenna</persName> with their two armies, but <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, who was eager to be part of the victory, fought with dubious results.

[92.3] Later, <persName n="519">Sertorius</persName> was besieged at Clunia, but by repeated sallies he was able to inflict as much damage on the besiegers as he received.

[92.4] It also contains accounts of the campaigns waged by proconsul <persName n="188">Gaius Scribonius Curio</persName> in Thrace against the Dardanians and of the many cruel acts committed by <persName n="519">Sertorius</persName> upon his men; on false accusations of treachery, he executed many of his friends and fellow-victims of the proscription.

From Book 93
[93.1] In Cilicia, proconsul <persName n="524">Servilius Isauricus</persName> conquered the Isaurians and captured several cities of the pirates.

[93.2] [75] King <persName n="383">Nicomedes</persName> of Bithynia made the Roman nation his heir and his kingdom was transformed into a province.

[93.3] <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> concluded a treaty with <persName n="519">Sertorius</persName> and declared war upon the Romans.

[93.4] Muster of the royal armies, infantry and naval; the occupation of Bithynia, how consul <persName n="325">Marcus Aurelius Cotta</persName> was defeated by the king at Calchedon; the achievements of <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> and <persName n="362">Metellus Pius</persName> against <persName n="519">Sertorius</persName>

[93.5] ... in every aspect of war and the art of soldiery, he was their equal [lacuna] and having made them to break off the siege of Calagurris, he forced them to retreat in different regions, <persName n="362">Metellus Pius</persName> to Hispania Ulterior, <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> to Gaul.

From Book 94
[94.1] [74] Consul <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName> successfully fought equestrian battles against <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> and launched several victorious campaigns, but restrained his mutinous soldiers, when they wanted battle.

[94.2] <persName n="147">Deiotarus</persName>, one of the tetrarchs of Gallograecia, crushed the deputies of <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> who tried to transfer the war to Phrygia.

[94.3] It also contains an account of <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>'s victorious war against <persName n="519">Sertorius</persName> in Hispania.

From Book 95
[95.1] In Thrace, proconsul <persName n="188">Gaius Curio</persName> subdued the Dardanians.

[95.2] [73] Seventy-four gladiators escaped from the school of <persName n="263">Lentulus</persName> at Capua, gathered a large number of slaves and workhouse prisoners, began a war under command of <persName n="136">Crixus</persName> and <persName n="542">Spartacus</persName>, and defeated the army of praetor <persName n="586">Varinius</persName> and his deputy <persName n="665">Claudius Glaber</persName>.

[95.3] Near the city of Cyzicus, proconsul <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName> destroyed the army of <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> with starvation and swords, expelled the king - now broken by several disasters of war and shipwreck - from Bithynia and forced him to make his escape to Pontus.

From Book 96
[96.1] Praetor <persName n="463">Quintus Arrius</persName> crushed <persName n="136">Crixus</persName>, the leader of the runaway slaves, and 20,000 men.

[96.2] [72 BCE] Consul <persName n="217">Gnaeus Lentulus</persName>, however, unsuccessfully fought against <persName n="542">Spartacus</persName>.

[96.3] Consul <persName n="294">Lucius Gellius</persName> and praetor <persName n="463">Quintus Arrius</persName> were defeated by the same.

[96.4] At a banquet, <persName n="519">Sertorius</persName> was killed by <persName n="403">Perpenna</persName>, <persName n="321">Marcus Antonius</persName> and other conspirators, during the eighth year of his command; he had been a great leader and against two commanders, <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> and <persName n="362">Metellus Pius</persName>, he had often been successful, although in the end, he changed into a savage and prodigal man.

[96.5] Leadership of his faction was transferred to <persName n="403">Perpenna</persName>, who was defeated, captured and killed by <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, after the latter had recovered the Spanish provinces in the almost tenth year after the beginning of the war.

[96.6] Proconsul <persName n="184">Gaius Cassius</persName> and praetor <persName n="220">Gnaeus Manlius</persName> unsuccessfully fought against <persName n="542">Spartacus</persName>, and the war was confined to praetor <persName n="138">Crassus</persName>.

From Book 97
[97.1] [71] Praetor <persName n="138">Crassus</persName> first fought victoriously with a part of the runaways, mainly Gauls and Germans, and killed 35,000 of them, including their leaders <persName n="103">Castus</persName> and <persName n="209">Gannicus</persName>.

[97.2] Then he completely defeated <persName n="542">Spartacus</persName>, who was killed with 60,000 people.

[97.3] Praetor <persName n="323">Marcus Antonius Creticus</persName> unsuccessfully fought a war against the Cretans, which came to an end with his own death.

[97.4] Proconsul <persName n="339">Marcus Lucullus</persName> subdued Thrace.

[97.5] <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName> successfully fought against <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> in Pontus. More than 60,000 enemies were killed.

[97.6] [70] <persName n="138">Crassus</persName> and <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> were made consuls (<persName n="423">Pompey</persName> after a special senatorial decree, because he had not occupied the quaestorship and was still a Roman knight), and reconstituted the tribunicial powers.

[97.7] Furthermore, praetor <persName n="325">Marcus Aurelius Cotta</persName> transferred control of the law courts to the Roman knights.

[97.8] His desperate position forced <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> to flee to king <persName n="565">Tigranes</persName> of Armenia.

From Book 98
[98.1] <persName n="312">Machares</persName>, the son of <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> and king of Bosphorus, received the title of friend from <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName>.

[98.2] [69] Censors <persName n="217">Gnaeus Lentulus</persName> and <persName n="294">Lucius Gellius</persName> conducted a strict censorship, removing 64 men from the Senate.

[98.3] They celebrated the ritual cleansing of the state and registered 900,000 citizens.

[98.4] On Sicily, praetor <persName n="300">Lucius Metellus</persName> successfully fought against the pirates.

[98.5] <persName n="465">Quintus Catulus</persName> rededicated the reconstructed temple of the Capitoline Jupiter, which had been destroyed by fire.

[98.6] In several battles in Armenia, <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName> routed <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, <persName n="565">Tigranes</persName> and their giant armies.

[98.7] Proconsul <persName n="360">Metellus Creticus</persName> took over the war against the Cretans and besieged the city of Cydonia.

[98.8] A deputy of <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName>, <persName n="797">Gaius Triarius</persName>, fought unsuccessfully against <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>.

[98.9] A revolt of soldiers who did not want to go any further, prevented <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName> from pursuing <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> and <persName n="565">Tigranes</persName> and obtaining the ultimate victory; involved were the two legions of <persName n="584">Valerius Flaccus</persName>, which deserted <persName n="311">Lucullus</persName> saying that their term of service was over.

From Book 99
[99.1] [68] Proconsul <persName n="360">Metellus Creticus</persName> captured Cnossus, Lyctus, Cydonia and many other cities.

[99.2] <persName n="306">Lucius Roscius</persName>, a tribune of the plebs , passed the law that the first fourteen rows in the theater were to be designated to the Roman knights.

[99.3] [67] <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> was ordered by a law, passed by the People's Assembly, to pursue the pirates, who had cut off the food supply. Within forty days he expelled them from the entire sea, brought the war against them to Cilicia, and gave land and cities to the pirates that surrendered to him.

[99.4] It also contains an account of <persName n="360">Metellus Creticus</persName>' war against the Cretans, and the letters exchanged between <persName n="360">Metellus Creticus</persName> and <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>.

[99.5] <persName n="360">Metellus Creticus</persName> complains that the glory of his victory was stolen by <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, who had sent a deputy to Crete to accept the surrender of the cities. <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> explained why this had to be done.

From Book 100
[100.1] [66] To the great indignation of the nobility, tribune <persName n="194">Gaius Manilius</persName> passed a law that transferred the [Third] Mithridatic War to <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>.

[100.2] ...note his speech was excellent.

[100.3] Having subdued the Cretans, <persName n="360">Metellus Creticus</persName> gave laws to their island, which had until then been independent.

[100.4] <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> renewed the friendship with the king of the Parthians, <persName n="412">Phraates III</persName>, to wage war against <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>.

[100.5] In an equestrian battle, <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> was defeated.

[100.6] It also contains an account of the war between king <persName n="412">Phraates III</persName> of the Parthians and <persName n="565">Tigranes</persName> of the Armenians, and after this of <persName n="566">Tigranes</persName> against his father.

From Book 101
[101.1] [66 BCE] After he had defeated <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> during the night, <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> forced him to flee to the Bosporan kingdom.

[101.2] <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> accepted the surrender of <persName n="565">Tigranes</persName> and restored him to his own kingdom, Armenia, after he had deprived him of Syria, Phoenicia, and Cilicia.

[101.3] There was a conspiracy by those who had been running for consul and had been condemned for bribery. They tried to kill the consuls, but the [First Catilinarian] conspiracy was suppressed.

[101.4] [65] <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, pursuing <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, reached the most distant and hitherto unknown peoples. The Hiberians and Albanians were defeated in battle when they denied him passage.

[101.5] It also contains an account of the flight of <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> through the country of the Colchians and Heniochians, and affairs in the Bosporan kingdom.

From Book 102
[102.1] <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> organized Pontus as a province.

[102.2] <persName n="407">Pharnaces</persName>, the son of <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, made war against his father

[102.3] and besieged him in his palace. When the poison <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName> took did not kill him, he asked help from a Gallic soldier named <persName n="77">Bitocus</persName>, who killed him.

[102.4] [63] <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> subdued the Jews and captured their shrine at Jerusalem, which had never before been violated.

[102.5] <persName n="605">Catiline</persName>, who had twice been defeated during consular elections, conspired with praetor <persName n="259">Lentulus</persName>, <persName n="109">Cethegus</persName> and many others. They wanted to kill the consuls and senators, set fire to the city, and overthrow the republic. Their army was ready in Etruria.

[102.6] The conspiracy was suppressed by the energy of <persName n="607">Cicero</persName>.

[102.7] When <persName n="605">Catiline</persName> had been expelled from the city, the other conspirators were executed.

From Book 103
[103.1] [62] <persName n="605">Catiline</persName> and his army were destroyed by proconsul <persName n="26">Antonius Hybrida</persName>.

[103.2] <persName n="117">Clodius</persName>, accused of having entered in woman's dress into a sanctuary that men were not allowed to enter, and of violating <persName n="878">Clodia</persName>, the wife of the priest <persName n="359">Metellus Celer</persName>, was acquitted.

[103.3] Praetor <persName n="202">Gaius Pontinus</persName> subdued the rebellious Allobrogians near Solo.

[103.4] <persName n="117">Clodius</persName> was transferred to the plebs.

[103.5] [61] <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> subdued the Lusitanians.

[103.6] [60] When this man was a candidate for the consulship, and wanted to seize control of the republic, a pact was concluded between the three leading citizens, <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, <persName n="138">Crassus</persName>, and <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>.

[103.7] [59] When <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> was consul, agrarian laws were passed after much strife, against the wishes of the Senate and the other consul, <persName n="75">Bibulus</persName>.

[103.8] Proconsul <persName n="26">Antonius Hybrida</persName> had little success in his war in Thrace.

[103.9] [58] <persName n="607">Cicero</persName> was exiled by a law of the tribune of the plebs <persName n="117">Clodius</persName>, because he had ordered the executions of Roman citizens without trial.

[103.10] <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>, who had gone to the Gallic provinces, subdued the Helvetians, a nomadic tribe that wanted to cross through <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>'s province Narbonensis, wishing to settle somewhere else.

[103.11] It also contains an account of the country of Gaul.

[103.12] When <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> celebrated a triumph over the children of <persName n="373">Mithridates</persName>, and <persName n="566">Tigranes</persName> son of <persName n="565">Tigranes</persName>, he was saluted by all those present with the surname The Great.

From Book 104
[104.1] The first part of this book contains an account of the country and customs of Germania.

[104.2] <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> led his army against the Germans, who had, commanded by <persName n="46">Ariovistus</persName>, invaded Gaul. This had been requested by the Aedui and Sequani, whose country had been occupied. With a speech, <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> suppressed panic among his soldiers, caused by fear of the new enemies. Having defeated the Germans in battle, he expelled them from Gaul.

[104.3] [57] <persName n="607">Cicero</persName>, backed by <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, tribune <persName n="368">Milo</persName> and others, returned from exile, amid great rejoicing on the part of the Senate and all Italy.

[104.4] The food supply was assigned to <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> for a period of five years.

[104.5] <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> accepted the surrender of the Belgian tribes of the Ambiani, Suessioni, Viruomandi, and Atrebates, whose numbers were very large, after he had defeated them in battle. He proceeded against the Nervians, another Belgian tribe, and fought a difficult battle against these aggressors, wiping them out so thoroughly that of 60,000 warriors only 500 survived, and of 600 aristocrats only 3.

[104.6] A law was carried that Cyprus should be organized as a province and the royal funds should be confiscated, and <persName n="104">Cato</persName>  was sent to administer the matter.

[104.7] King <persName n="439">Ptolemy XII Auletes</persName> of Egypt left his realm and came to Rome after he had been maltreated by his subjects.

[104.8] [56] <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> defeated the Veneti, a tribe near the Ocean, in a naval battle. It also contains an account of the successful wars of his deputies.

From Book 105
[105.1] When the elections were vetoed by tribune <persName n="185">Gaius Cato</persName>, the senators put on their mourning cloaks.

[105.2] <persName n="104">Cato</persName>  ran for praetor, but was defeated. <persName n="591">Vatinius</persName> was elected.

[105.3] [55] When this same man tried to obstruct a law in which provinces were allotted to the consuls for five years (Hispania to <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, Syria and the Parthian war to <persName n="138">Crassus</persName>), he was put into irons by tribune <persName n="579">Trebonius</persName>, who had proposed the law.

[105.4] [54] Proconsul <persName n="176">Gabinius</persName> brought <persName n="439">Ptolemy XII Auletes</persName> back to the kingdom of Egypt, and expelled <persName n="41">Archelaus</persName>, who had proclaimed himself king as husband of queen <persName n="73">Berenice IV</persName>.

[105.5] After he had defeated German tribes in Gaul, <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> crossed the Rhine and subdued a nearby part of Germania. He proceeded across the Ocean to Britain, at first with little success because of bad weather, but on a second occasion with better luck. He killed a large number of enemies and subdued a part of the island.

From Book 106
[106.1] [54 BCE] <persName n="245">Julia</persName>, <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>'s daughter and <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>'s wife, died, and the people allowed her the honor of a burial on the field of Mars.

[106.2] Several Gallic tribes, commanded by king <persName n="17">Ambiorix</persName> of the Eburones, revolted.

[106.3] <persName n="131">Cotta</persName> and <persName n="570">Titurius</persName>, <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>'s deputies, were besieged with the army they commanded, and killed.

[106.4] And when the camps of the other legions were also besieged and defended with difficulty, the camp of <persName n="466">Quintus Cicero</persName> among the Treverians, was after a battle liberated by <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>.

[106.5] [53] <persName n="138">Crassus</persName> crossed the river Euphrates, carried the war to the Parthian Empire, and was defeated in a battle [near Carrhae] in which his son <persName n="447">Publius Crassus</persName> also fell. With the remains of his army, he occupied a hill, and was summoned to a conference by the enemy leader, <persName n="551">Surena</persName>, as if to speak about a truce. However, he was captured and killed in a struggle to avoid suffering the indignity of remaining alive.

From Book 107
[107.1] <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> overcame the Treverians in Gaul, and crossed into Germania for the second time, but when he did not meet an enemy, he returned to Gaul. He subdued the Eburones and other rebellious tribes and pursued <persName n="17">Ambiorix</persName> when he tried to make his escape.

[107.2] [52] <persName n="117">Clodius</persName> was killed on the Via Appia, near Bovillae, by <persName n="368">Milo</persName>, a candidate for the consulship. <persName n="117">Clodius</persName> was cremated by the plebs in the building of the Senate.

[107.3] There were violent and armed riots among the candidates for the consulship, <persName n="240">Hypsaeus</persName>, <persName n="363">Metellus Scipio</persName>, and <persName n="368">Milo</persName>. To suppress these, <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> was deputized... and, although he was absent, elected consul for the third time, without colleague. This had never happened before.

[107.4] After an investigation of the death of <persName n="117">Clodius</persName> had been decreed, <persName n="368">Milo</persName> was condemned by the court and sent into exile.

[107.5] A law was introduced that <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> could be candidate for the consulship while he was absent; this was not to <persName n="104">Cato</persName> 's liking, and he spoke against it.

[107.6] It also contains an account of <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>'s actions against the Gauls, who had revolted almost without exception under <persName n="593">Vercingetorix</persName>, leader of the Arvernians, and contains accounts of difficult sieges of several towns, such as Avaricum of the Bituriges and Gergovia of the Arvernians.

From Book 108
[108.1] <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> defeated all Gallic tribes that were in arms at Alesia, and accepted their surrender.

[108.2] [51] <persName n="606">Cassius</persName>, quaestor of <persName n="138">Curio</persName>, defeated the Parthians, who had invaded Syria.

[108.3] <persName n="104">Cato</persName> was defeated when he stood for the consulship. Instead, <persName n="527">Servius Sulpicius Rufus</persName> and <persName n="330">Marcus Claudius Marcellus</persName> were elected.

[108.4] <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> subdued the Bellovaces and other Gallic tribes.

[108.5] [50] It also contains an account of the conflict between the consuls about who they should send as successor of <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>. Consul <persName n="330">Marcus Claudius Marcellus</persName> proposed to the Senate that <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> should return to run for consul, although a law had been passed that he was to rule his provinces until the time of his consulship had come. The book also contains an account of the war conducted by <persName n="75">Bibulus</persName> in Syria.

From Book 109 (which is the first dealing with the civil war)
[109.1] The causes and beginning of the civil war are described, together with the conflict about sending out a successor to <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>, who refused to disband his armies unless <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> disbanded his.

[109.2] It also contains an account of the actions of the tribune of the plebs <persName n="138">Curio</persName>, who was first against <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>, but later supported his case.

[109.3] When the Senate had decided that <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> was to be replaced, the tribunes <persName n="27">Antony</persName> and <persName n="464">Quintus Cassius</persName>, who tried to obstruct the senatorial decision, were expelled from the city. The consuls and <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> received special powers from the Senate, to see to it that no harm befell the republic.

[109.4] [49] <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> entered Italy with an army to wage war against his enemies. He captured Corfinium together with <persName n="293">Lucius Domitius</persName> and <persName n="451">Publius Lentulus</persName>, set them free, and expelled <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> and the other members of his faction from Italy.

From Book 110 (which is the second dealing with the civil war)
[110.1] <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> laid siege to Marseilles, which had closed its gates, but left the siege of the city to his deputies <persName n="579">Trebonius</persName> and <persName n="144">Decimus Brutus</persName> and went to Hispania, where he accepted the surrender of <persName n="8">Afranius</persName> and <persName n="405">Petreius</persName>, deputies of <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, and seven legions at Ilerda. He let them all go unharmed. Even <persName n="556">Terentius Varro</persName>, another deputy of <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, and his army were brought into <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>'s power.

[110.2] He gave the people of Gades the citizenship.

[110.3] The Massiliotes, which had been defeated in two naval battles, surrendered themselves to <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> after a long siege.

[110.4] <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>'s deputy <persName n="178">Gaius Antonius</persName> fought unsuccessfully against the Pompeians in Illyria and was captured.

[110.5] In this war, several Opiterginians from across the Po (<persName n="89">Caesar</persName>'s auxiliary troops) killed each other rather than be captured when their raft was surrendered by enemy ships.

[110.6] <persName n="138">Curio</persName>, <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>'s deputy in Africa, fought successfully against <persName n="589">Varus</persName>, the leader of the Pompeian faction, but was killed with his army by <persName n="242">Juba</persName>, the king of Mauretania.

[110.7] [48] <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> crossed to Greece.

From Book 111 (which is the third dealing with the civil war)
[111.1] [48 BCE] Praetor <persName n="493">Rufus</persName>, who had provoked riots in the city by inciting the plebs with the prospect of a debt cancellation, was expelled from office and from the city, and joined the exile <persName n="368">Milo</persName>, who was building an army of runaway slaves.

[111.2] Both of them were killed when they tried to stir up war.

[111.3] Queen <persName n="114">Cleopatra</persName> of Egypt was exiled by her brother <persName n="440">Ptolemy XIII</persName>.

[111.4] Because of the avarice and cruelty of propraetor <persName n="464">Quintus Cassius</persName>, the inhabitants of Cordoba in Hispania, together with the two legions of <persName n="556">Terentius Varro</persName>, abandoned the cause of <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>.

[111.5] <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> was besieged at Dyrrhachium by <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> and, after storming the latter's forts with great losses to the other side, freed himself from the siege and transferred the war to Thessaly, where his army was defeated at Pharsalus.

[111.6] <persName n="607">Cicero</persName> remained in <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>'s camp, because there was never a man less suited to war than he. <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> pardoned all enemies who put themselves in the hands of the victor.

From Book 112 (which is the fourth dealing with the civil war)
[112.1] It tells about the panic and flight of the members of the defeated party to various parts of the world.

[112.2] When <persName n="423">Pompey</persName> went to Egypt, he was, by order of king <persName n="440">Ptolemy XIII</persName> (<persName n="423">Pompey</persName>'s own pupil) but at the instigation of <persName n="434">Pothinus</persName> and the king's influential teacher <persName n="558">Theodotus</persName>, murdered in a small bark, before he could set foot ashore, by <persName n="1">Achillas</persName>, who had been commanded to commit this crime.

[112.3] <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>'s wife <persName n="122">Cornelia</persName> and his son <persName n="538">Sextus Pompey</persName> escaped to Cyprus.

[112.4] When <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> arrived in pursuit on the third day, <persName n="558">Theodotus</persName> showed him <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>'s head and ring, but <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> was offended and wept.

[112.5] Without running any risks he entered a riotous Alexandria.

[112.6] <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>, who had been made dictator, restored <persName n="114">Cleopatra</persName> as queen of Egypt and he won through - at great personal risk - when <persName n="440">Ptolemy XIII</persName> attacked him, following the advice of the very men who had advised him to kill <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>.

[112.7] When <persName n="440">Ptolemy XIII</persName> made his escape, his ship capsized in the Nile.

[112.8] It also contains an account of the difficult march of <persName n="104">Cato</persName> and his legions across the African desert, and an unsuccessful war against <persName n="407">Pharnaces</persName> waged by <persName n="215">Gnaeus Domitius Calvinus</persName>.

From Book 113 (which is the fifth dealing with the civil war)
[113.1] [47] The Pompeian faction had consolidated its position in Africa and after <persName n="104">Cato</persName>  had declined an offer of joint command, the sole command was given to <persName n="363">Metellus Scipio</persName>.

[113.2] When a debate took place about the sack of the city of Utica, whose citizens favored <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>, and <persName n="104">Cato</persName>  maintained that it should not be done whereas <persName n="242">Juba</persName> argued for its destruction, <persName n="104">Cato</persName>  was elected as the town's protector and warden.

[113.3] <persName n="221">Gnaeus Pompey</persName>, son of <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, assembled an army in Hispania, and because neither <persName n="8">Afranius</persName> nor <persName n="405">Petreius</persName> wanted to be commander, he personally started the war against <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>.

[113.4] King <persName n="407">Pharnaces</persName> of Pontus, the son of <persName n="372">Mithridates</persName>, was defeated without the slightest delay in the campaign.

[113.5] The tribune of the plebs <persName n="152">Dolabella</persName> caused unrest when he proposed a law to cancel debts, and the plebs started to revolt. However, <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, the master of horse, sent soldiers into the city and 800 people were killed.

[113.6] <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> allowed his veterans, who were rebellious and demanded their discharge, what they asked, and crossed into Africa, where he fought at great personal risk against king <persName n="242">Juba</persName>'s men.

From Book 114 (which is the sixth dealing with the civil war)
[114.1] [46] <persName n="85">Caecilius Bassus</persName>, a Roman knight of the Pompeian faction, provoked a war in Syria, and <persName n="534">Sextus Caesar</persName>, abandoned by a legion that had transferred its allegiance to <persName n="85">Caecilius Bassus</persName>, was killed.

[114.2] <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> defeated the praetor <persName n="363">Metellus Scipio</persName> and <persName n="242">Juba</persName> at Thapsus and captured their camp.

[114.3] When <persName n="104">Cato</persName> received this news in Utica, he stabbed himself and although his son intervened and tried to rescue him, he reopened the wound that was being nursed, and died at the age of forty-eight.

[114.4] <persName n="405">Petreius</persName> killed <persName n="242">Juba</persName> and himself.

[114.5] <persName n="363">Metellus Scipio</persName> was captured on his ship, and added to his honorable death honorable last words.

[114.6] When his enemies asked him how the general was doing, <persName n="363">Metellus Scipio</persName> replied "the general is doing fine".

[114.7] <persName n="163">Faustus</persName> and <persName n="8">Afranius</persName> were killed.

[114.8] <persName n="104">Cato</persName>'s son <persName n="105">Cato</persName>was pardoned.

[114.9] <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>'s deputy commander <persName n="144">Decimus Brutus</persName> won a battle in Gaul and defeated the rebellious Bellovaces.

From Book 115 (which is the seventh dealing with the civil war)
[115.1] <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> celebrated four triumphs: for his victories in Gaul, Egypt, Pontus, and Africa. He also gave a banquet and several shows.

[115.2] At the request of the Senate, he allowed former consul <persName n="330">Marcus Claudius Marcellus</persName> to return.

[115.3] However, <persName n="330">Marcus Claudius Marcellus</persName> could not benefit from this kindness, because he was murdered in Athens by his client <persName n="218">Gnaeus Magius</persName> .

[115.4] <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> had the citizens counted, and 150,000 people were registered.

[115.5] He set out for Hispania to fight against <persName n="221">Gnaeus Pompey</persName>, and after both sides had conducted several operations and stormed several cities, <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> won at great risk his greatest victory near the town of Munda.

[115.6] <persName n="221">Gnaeus Pompey</persName> was killed and <persName n="538">Sextus Pompey</persName> made his escape.

From Book 116 (which is the eighth dealing with the civil war)
[116.1] [45 BCE] <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> celebrated a fifth triumph, for his Spanish victory.

[116.2] [44] After the Senate decreed many of the highest honors (such as the right to be called "father of the fatherland" together with an eternal inviolability and dictatorship), several grudges rose against him: because he did not rise from his throne in front of the temple of Venus Genetrix when the senators arrived to present him with these honors; because, when his fellow consul <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, dancing with the luperci, placed a diadem on his head, he placed it on his throne; and because he expelled the tribunes of the plebs <persName n="156">Epidius Marullus</persName> and <persName n="91">Caesetius Flavus</persName> from office after they had caused hostility towards him, arguing that he was aiming at one man rule.

[116.3] For these reasons, a conspiracy was formed against him, its leaders being <persName n="81">Brutus</persName> and <persName n="606">Cassius</persName>, and, from <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>'s own men, <persName n="144">Decimus Brutus</persName> and <persName n="579">Trebonius</persName>. With twenty-three stabs he was murdered in the Curia Pompeia, and the Capitol was occupied by the assassins.

[116.4] The Senate decreed an amnesty for the murder, and when the besieged conspirators had received the children of <persName n="27">Antony</persName> and <persName n="264">Lepidus</persName> as hostages, they descended from the Capitol.

[116.5] By <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>'s will, <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, the grandson of his sister, was adopted as his son and made heir to half his estate.

[116.6] When <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>'s corpse was brought to the field of Mars, it was burned in front of the Speaker's platform by the plebs.

[116.7] The office of dictator was banned forever.

[116.8] One <persName n="16">Chiamates</persName>, a man of the lowest rank, pretending to be the son of <persName n="602">Marius</persName>, caused disturbances among the credulous plebs, but was killed.

From Book 117
[117.1] <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> arrived from Epirus (he had been sent there in advance by <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> to wage war in Macedonia), and after all kind of favorable signs, he accepted the name of xxxx.

[117.2] In an atmosphere of confusion and disturbance, <persName n="264">Lepidus</persName> accepted the office of pontifex maximus.

[117.3] The consul <persName n="27">Antony</persName> recklessly tried to dominate the stage and carried a law concerning changes in the assignment of provinces by violence. He intensely hurt <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, who came to ask for help against the assassins of his great-uncle. As a result, <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> started to acquire resources against him in the colonies of the veterans, which he would use for himself and the republic.

[117.4] The Fourth and the Martian legions indeed transferred their loyalty from <persName n="27">Antony</persName> to <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>,  and because of the savage behavior of <persName n="27">Antony</persName> (who killed several suspects in his camp) others followed.

[117.5] With an army, <persName n="144">Decimus Brutus</persName> occupied Modena, in order to head off <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, who was making for Cisalpine Gaul.

[117.6] It also contains an account of the scattering of men on both sides to take over provinces, and describes other preparations for war.

From Book 118
[118.1] In Greece, <persName n="81">Brutus</persName>, pretending to act for the benefit of the state and the campaign against <persName n="27">Antony</persName> that was undertaken, obtained the army of <persName n="591">Vatinius</persName> and the province as well.

[118.2] The Senate gave <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, who as a private citizen had built an army, the powers of a propraetor and the ornaments of a consul, and promised that he would be made senator.

[118.3] <persName n="27">Antony</persName> besieged <persName n="144">Decimus Brutus</persName> at Modena, and the envoys sent by the Senate to negotiate peace were unsuccessful,

[118.4] so the Roman people accepted the military dress.

[118.5] In Epirus, <persName n="81">Brutus</persName> overcame praetor <persName n="178">Gaius Antonius</persName> and his army.

From Book 119
[119.1] By the treachery of <persName n="152">Dolabella</persName>, <persName n="579">Trebonius</persName> was murdered in Asia.

[119.2] Because of this crime, <persName n="152">Dolabella</persName> was declared to be an enemy by the Senate.

[119.3] [43] After consul <persName n="396">Pansa</persName> had unsuccessfully fought against <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, consul <persName n="234">Hirtius</persName> arrived with his army, defeated the troops of <persName n="27">Antony</persName> and brought the fortunes of both sides in balance again.

[119.4] <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, defeated by <persName n="234">Hirtius</persName> and <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, fled to Gaul, where he joined <persName n="264">Lepidus</persName> and the legions under his command; the Senate declared him and every soldier in his army an enemy.

[119.5] <persName n="234">Hirtius</persName>, who had been killed in the camp of the enemy after his victory, and <persName n="396">Pansa</persName>, who had died from wounds received during his defeat, were buried on the Field of Mars.

[119.6] The Senate was hardly grateful to <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, who was the only one of three leaders to survive: it voted the honor of a triumph to <persName n="144">Decimus Brutus</persName>, who had been freed from the siege of Modena by <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, and made no satisfying reference to <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> and his soldiers.

[119.7] Therefore, <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, on advise by <persName n="264">Lepidus</persName>, reconciled himself with <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, marched on Rome with his army, and, surprising everyone who was against him, was made consul at the age of nineteen.

From Book 120
[120.1] As consul, <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> carried a law to prosecute those who had been involved in the murder of his father <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>; under the terms of this law, <persName n="81">Brutus</persName>, <persName n="606">Cassius</persName>, and <persName n="144">Decimus Brutus</persName> were condemned in their absence.

[120.2] <persName n="55">Asinius Pollio</persName> and <persName n="378">Plancus</persName> as well joined <persName n="27">Antony</persName> with their armies and made him stronger; and <persName n="144">Decimus Brutus</persName>, whom the Senate had ordered <persName n="27">Antony</persName> to pursue, was deserted by his legions, fled, and was put to death by <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, into whose power he had come, by a Sequanian named <persName n="99">Capenus</persName>.

[120.3] <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> made his peace with <persName n="27">Antony</persName> and <persName n="264">Lepidus</persName>. For five years, they were to be triumvirs for the restoration of the republic, and opponents of <persName n="264">Lepidus</persName>, <persName n="27">Antony</persName> and <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> were to be proscribed.

[120.4] Many Roman knights, and the names of 130 senators, were listed, such as <persName n="275">Lucius Aemilius Paulus</persName> (<persName n="264">Lepidus</persName>' brother), <persName n="282">Lucius Caesar</persName> (an uncle of <persName n="27">Antony</persName>), and <persName n="607">Cicero</persName>.

[120.5] <persName n="607">Cicero</persName> was killed by <persName n="429">Popillius</persName>, a legionary soldier, at the age of sixty-three. His head and right hand were exposed on the Speaker's platform.

[120.6] It also contains an account of <persName n="81">Brutus</persName>' acts in Greece.

From Book 121
[121.0] Reportedly published after the death of <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>

[121.1] [43 BCE] <persName n="606">Cassius</persName>, who had been sent by the Senate to pursue <persName n="152">Dolabella</persName> (who was declared an enemy of the state), used the authority of the republic to obtain the three armies that were stationed in the province of Syria, laid siege to the town of Laodicea and forced <persName n="152">Dolabella</persName> to commit suicide.

[121.2] <persName n="178">Gaius Antonius</persName> was captured and executed too, by command of <persName n="81">Brutus</persName>.

From Book 122
[122.1] For some time, <persName n="81">Brutus</persName> waged a successful war against the Thracians, and when all the provinces and armies across the sea were in his and <persName n="606">Cassius</persName>' power, they came together in Smyrna to make plans for the future war.

[122.2] Together, they pardoned <persName n="341">Marcus Messala</persName>, convinced by his brother <persName n="442">Publicola</persName>.

From Book 123
[123.1] [42] <persName n="538">Sextus Pompey</persName>, son of <persName n="423">Pompey</persName>, who had assembled exiles and runaways from Epirus, and had for a long time been active as pirate, without having a real base, first captured Messina (a town on Sicily) and then the whole province, and, having killed governor <persName n="422">Pompeius Bithynicus</persName>, he defeated <persName n="501">Salvidienus</persName>, who had been sent by <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, in a naval battle.

[123.2] <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> and <persName n="27">Antony</persName> crossed over to Greece with their armies to wage war against <persName n="81">Brutus</persName> and <persName n="606">Cassius</persName>.

[123.3] In Africa, <persName n="125">Cornificius</persName> fought against <persName n="574">Titus Sextius</persName>, the leader of the faction of <persName n="606">Cassius</persName>, and defeated him.

From Book 124
[124.1] At Philippi, <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> and <persName n="27">Antony</persName> fought against <persName n="81">Brutus</persName> and <persName n="606">Cassius</persName>. The outcome was inconclusive because on both sides the right wing won and on both sides the camp was taken by those who had been victorious.

[124.2] But the death of <persName n="606">Cassius</persName> tipped the scales. He had been on the wing that had been defeated and, believing that the whole army had been beaten, chose death.

[124.3] On the next day, <persName n="81">Brutus</persName> was defeated, and he put an end to his life, asking Strato (who was fleeing too), to drive his sword through him. He was about forty years old.

[124.4] ...note among whom <persName n="239">Quintus Hortensius</persName> was killed.

From Book 125
[125.1] [41] <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, leaving <persName n="27">Antony</persName> overseas (the provinces in that part of the empire had been placed under his command), returned to Italy and gave land to his veterans.

[125.2] At great danger he suppressed rebellions in his army, which certain soldiers, corrupted by <persName n="172">Fulvia</persName>, the wife of <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, had stirred up against its general.

[125.3] Consul <persName n="278">Lucius Antonius</persName>, brother of <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, launched a war against <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>.

[125.4] The peoples whose country had been given to the veterans, had sided with him, and he defeated <persName n="264">Lepidus</persName>, who was responsible for the defense of the city, and forced his way into Rome.

From Book 126
[126.1] <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> was only twenty-three when he laid siege to <persName n="278">Lucius Antonius</persName> in the town of Perugia and prevented several break-outs, and when hunger forced him into surrender, [40] <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> pardoned him and all his soldiers, but sacked Perugia. Without bloodshed, he brought the armies of both sides in this war under his command.

From Book 127
[127.1] The Parthians, commanded by <persName n="253">Labienus</persName>, who belonged to the faction of the Pompeians, invaded Syria and, having defeated <persName n="143">Decidius Saxa</persName>, a deputy of <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, occupied the entire province.

[127.2] When Mark <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, in order to make war against <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> his wife <persName n="172">Fulvia</persName>, so that there was no obstacle to an agreement between the leaders, made peace with <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> and married his sister <persName n="388">Octavia</persName>.

[127.3] He exposed by his own evidence how <persName n="501">Salvidienus</persName> was making criminal plans against <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>; he was condemned and committed suicide.

[127.4] <persName n="458">Publius Ventidius Bassus</persName>, a deputy of <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, defeated the Parthians in battle and drove them out of Syria, after their commander <persName n="253">Labienus</persName> had been killed.

[127.5] [39] Because an enemy close to Italy, <persName n="538">Sextus Pompey</persName>, occupied Sicily and threatened the grain trade, <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> and <persName n="27">Antony</persName> concluded, at his demand, a peace treaty with him, so that he could rule Sicily as a province.

[127.6] It also contains an account of the troubles in Africa and the wars that were fought over there.

From Book 128
[128.1] [38] When <persName n="538">Sextus Pompey</persName> through piracy made the sea dangerous again and did not maintain the peace he had agreed upon, <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> accepted the necessary war against him, and fought two naval battles, with a dubious outcome.

[128.2] <persName n="458">Publius Ventidius Bassus</persName>, a deputy of Mark <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, defeated the Parthians in Syria and killed their leader.

[128.3] [37] The Jews were also defeated by a deputy of <persName n="27">Antony</persName>.

[128.4] It also contains an account of the preparations of the Sicilian war.

From Book 129
[129.1] [36] Naval battles with varying outcomes were fought against <persName n="538">Sextus Pompey</persName>, in the following way: of the two navies of <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, the one, whose admiral was <persName n="9">Agrippa</persName>, was victorious, but the other, commanded by <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, was destroyed and the soldiers that had been set ashore were exposed to grave danger.

[129.2] The defeated <persName n="538">Sextus Pompey</persName> fled to [the interior of] Sicily.

[129.3] When <persName n="264">Lepidus</persName>, who had arrived from Africa as if to support <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> in his struggle against <persName n="538">Sextus Pompey</persName>, launched a war against <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, he was abandoned by his army, deprived of his triumviral powers, but successfully begged for his life.

[129.4] <persName n="9">Agrippa</persName> received a naval crown from <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, an honor that no one had received before.

From Book 130
[130.1] Living a life of pleasure with <persName n="114">Cleopatra</persName>, <persName n="27">Antony</persName> invaded Media rather late, and brought war to Parthia with eighteen legions and 16,000 horsemen; having lost two legions and failing to achieve success in any enterprise, he retreated, pursued by Parthians, and after immense confusion and great danger, reached Armenia, having covered in his flight three hundred miles, in twenty-one days.

[130.2] Because of tempests, he lost about 8,000 men.

[130.3] (Like the Parthian war that he had undertaken so unluckily, it was his own mistake that he encountered these tempests, because he refused to winter in Armenia but instead hurried to <persName n="114">Cleopatra</persName>.)

From Book 131
[131.1] [35] Although <persName n="538">Sextus Pompey</persName> had put himself under the protection of <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, he prepared for war against him in Asia, but was surprised and executed by his deputies.

[131.2] After <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> had overcome a very damaging insurrection of veterans, he defeated the Iapydes, Dalmatians, and Pannonians.

[131.3] [34] <persName n="27">Antony</persName> ordered <persName n="52">Artavasdes</persName>, the king of Armenia, whom he had given a free-conduct, to be thrown into chains, and gave the Armenian kingdom to his son <persName n="11">Alexander Helios</persName>, who was born of <persName n="114">Cleopatra</persName>; he had been captivated by her for some time, but now began to treat her as his wife.

From Book 132
[132.1] <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> subdued the Dalmatians in Illyricum.

[132.2] [33] When <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, because of his love for <persName n="114">Cleopatra</persName>, with whom he had two sons (<persName n="437">Ptolemy Philadelphus</persName> and <persName n="11">Alexander Helios</persName>), did neither want to come to the city nor lay down his powers when term of the triumvirate had ended, but instead prepared for war against the city and Italy, and gathered for this purpose as many naval as land forces, [32] and sent a letter of divorce to <persName n="388">Octavia</persName>, <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>'s sister, [31] <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> crossed to Epirus with an army.

[132.3] After this, an account is given of the naval and equestrian battles, in which <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> was victorious.

From Book 133
[133.1] [30] <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, defeated in a naval battle near Actium, fled to Alexandria and, besieged by <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, in a desperate situation and above all misguided by a false rumor about the death of <persName n="114">Cleopatra</persName>, killed himself.

[133.2] After <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> had reduced Alexandria, and <persName n="114">Cleopatra</persName>, to avoid falling in the victor's hands, had died by her own hand, [29] he returned to the city to celebrate three triumphs: one over Illyricum, a second for the victory at Actium, and a third one over <persName n="114">Cleopatra</persName>; this was the end of the civil wars, in their twenty-second year.

[133.3] [28] <persName n="338">Marcus Lepidus</persName> (the son of the <persName n="264">Lepidus</persName> who had been triumvir) conspired against <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> to make war, but it was suppressed and he was killed.

From Book 134
[134.1] [27] When <persName n="61">Augustus</persName> had settled all affairs and all provinces had been solidly organized, he was called xxxx; in his honor, the month Sextilis received the same name.

[134.2] When he was holding assizes at Narbo, he conducted a census in the three provinces of Gaul, which his father <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> had subdued.

[134.3] An account is given of the war fought by <persName n="332">Marcus Crassus</persName> against the Basterni, Moesians and other peoples.

From Book 135
[135.1] [25] An account is given of the wars fought against the Thracians by <persName n="332">Marcus Crassus</persName> and against the Hispanians by <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>; the Salassi, a tribe from the Alps, were also subdued.

[136-137] Of books 136 and 137, the excerpts are missing.

[136] [[20] Peace was made with the Parthians and the standards, which had been lost by <persName n="138">Curio</persName> and later by <persName n="27">Antony</persName>, were received back from their king.]

[137] [[16] <persName n="563">Tiberius</persName>, the brother of of <persName n="154">Drusus</persName>, subdued the Dalmatians and Pannonians.

From Book 138
[138.1] [15] The Raetians were subdued by <persName n="563">Tiberius</persName> and <persName n="154">Drusus</persName>, the stepsons of <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>.

[138.2] [12] <persName n="9">Agrippa</persName>, the son-in-law of <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, died.

[138.3] A census was organized by <persName n="154">Drusus</persName>.

From Book 139
[139.1] The Germanic tribes living on this side of the Rhine and across the Rhine were attacked by <persName n="154">Drusus</persName>, and the uprising in Gaul, caused by the census, was suppressed.

[139.2] An altar was dedicated to the divine <persName n="89">Caesar</persName> at the confluence of the Saône and Rhône, and a priest was appointed, <persName n="594">Vercondaridubnus</persName>.

From Book 140
[140.1] [11] The Thracians were subdued by <persName n="303">Lucius Piso</persName>; an account is given of the subjugation of the Cherusci, Tencteri, Chauci, and other Germanic people across the Rhine by <persName n="154">Drusus</persName>.

[140.2] <persName n="388">Octavia</persName>, the sister of <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>, died, after losing her son <persName n="316">Marcellus</persName>, whose monuments are the theater and the portico dedicated in his name.

From Book 141
[141.1] [10] An account is given of the war that <persName n="154">Drusus</persName> fought against the peoples across the Rhine.

[141.2] Among other important people fighting over there were <persName n="608">Chumstinctus</persName> and <persName n="44">Avectius</persName>, military tribunes from the tribe of the Nervians.

From Book 142
[142.1] [9] An account is given of the war that <persName n="154">Drusus</persName> fought against the German tribes across the Rhine.

[142.2] <persName n="154">Drusus</persName> died from a fracture caused by the fall of his horse on his leg, thirty days after the accident.

[142.3] His body was brought to Rome by his brother <persName n="563">Tiberius</persName>, who had hurriedly arrived when he had received news about the illness; the body was buried in the tomb of <persName n="89">Caesar</persName>.

[142.4] The eulogy was pronounced by his stepfather <persName n="61">Augustus</persName>.

[142.5] During the funeral, many distinctions were conferred on him.
 </document>
